<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Aaron Meurer's Blog</title><link>http://asmeurer.github.io/</link><description>My blog</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 20:45:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>SciPy 2014</title><link>http://asmeurer.github.io/posts/scipy-2014/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just finished &lt;a href="https://conference.scipy.org/scipy2014/"&gt;SciPy 2014&lt;/a&gt;, a
week-long conference in Austin, TX for scientific computing with Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is my third SciPy (I have been to
&lt;a href="https://asmeurersympy.wordpress.com/2011/07/17/the-scipy-2011-conference/"&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://asmeurersympy.wordpress.com/2013/07/02/scipy-2013/"&gt;2013&lt;/a&gt;). This
year, the conference was noticeably larger. Last year there were
&lt;a href="http://andy.terrel.us/blog/2013/07/05/scipy2013-recap/"&gt;~350 people&lt;/a&gt;, this
year, there were
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/scopatz/status/488370261150818304"&gt;~450 people&lt;/a&gt;.  Aside
from there being a lot more people, and the main keynotes taking place in a
larger room, the most noticeable consequence of this is that there were three
days of talks this year, and three concurrent tracks of talks all three
days. The conference consisted of two days of tutorials, three days of talks,
and two days of sprints, running from July 5 to July 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference started on Sunday with tutorials. I gave a tutorial on SymPy
with &lt;a href="http://matthewrocklin.com/blog/"&gt;Matthew Rocklin&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://www.moorepants.info/blog/"&gt;Jason Moore&lt;/a&gt;. The videos are on YouTube
(parts &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lgp442bibDM"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_PTe10whFKo"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qleGSnrnxgc"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=04AGOl1P2U4"&gt;four&lt;/a&gt;).  I gave tutorials for
SymPy the previous two times I was at SciPy, although with different people
(with Mateusz Paprocki in 2011 and
&lt;a href="http://ondrejcertik.blogspot.com/"&gt;Ondřej Čertík&lt;/a&gt; in 2013). I really enjoy
seeing new people learn about SymPy, and working with Matthew Rocklin, who is
a very good speaker and teacher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also attended the tutorial on PyDy by Jason Moore, Gilbert Gede, and
Obinna Nwanna (parts &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lWbeuDwYVto"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1-KqRvNX0po"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;).  This tutorial was
also well done, and I highly recommend it if you are interested in Newtonian
mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I unfortunately was unable to attend any of the other tutorials, but I heard
good things about them, especially the
&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vWkgEddb4-A"&gt;Julia tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Talks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Tuesday to Thursday were talks. The quality of talks this year was very
high. The SciPy talks have always been high quality talks, but this year I
felt that they were particularly good. I don't think I saw a bad talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I can't really recommend the good talks that I saw without recommending
all of them. You should go to YouTube and the
&lt;a href="https://conference.scipy.org/scipy2014/schedule/"&gt;SciPy schedule&lt;/a&gt; and watch
any talk that looks interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I therefore am going to recommend watching the very best talks.  Two talks in
particular stood out to me as the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First is Greg Wilson's Thursday keynote, which is among the best talks I've
ever seen from any conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/1e26rp6qPbA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greg mentions a lot of ideas, quite a few of which are controversial, which I
think always makes for an interesting talk. Most of the talk is about
pedagogy, especially regarding his experiences at
&lt;a href="http://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt;. Some things he posited:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is actually good research about what methods work and don't work in
  teaching. He referenced
  &lt;a href="http://www.slideshare.net/richardcookau/john-hattie-effect-sizes-on-achievement"&gt;this presentation&lt;/a&gt;,
  which lists just about every possible pedagogical effect, and the net
  difference that it has on students, based on over 50,000 studies. For
  example, individualized instruction has a very small positive effect,
  whereas teacher feedback has a very large positive effect. Since each takes
  time and resources, we should focus on those effects that have the highest
  impact. Greg pointed out that web-based learning has very little positive
  effect, and hence is a waste of time and money. The most helpful effect is
  removing disruptive students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I liked the quote, "if you want more computing in high
school, you have to tell me what to take out."  People like to go on that
schools need to teach more of this or more of that, and computing and
programming tends to be high on that list these days, but anyone who does
not discuss what things should be removed from the curriculum, which is
already quite full, is not being honest about the discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other big point Greg made is that we need more incremental massive
  collaboration in teaching. This is the same model that has built open source
  and Wikipedia, but is mostly absent from teaching. Incremental change is
  important here, as well. It is more useful for someone to contribute fixes
  to existing lesson plans, so that they become better for the students, but
  in his experience, people are much more willing to add new lessons.  Greg
  calls for a "culture of patching". If incremental change could be adopted in
  teaching, teachers could aggregate methods and lesson plans, removing the
  massive duplication, and most importantly, making teaching materials that
  actually work for students to learn. Greg Wilson asks why open source and
  Wikipedia are able to thrive on massive &lt;em&gt;incremental&lt;/em&gt; change, but teaching
  is not, a question he hasn't found the answer to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My thought on the matter is that unlike writing software or collecting and
presenting facts, pedagogy is very difficult. If I contribute a patch to an
open source project that fixes a bug, I can run the tests to see if my fix
is "correct". If I fix an incorrect fact on Wikipedia, it is less easy, but
I can still cite and check references to make sure it is correct.  But for
teaching, it is very difficult to know what methods work and what don't, and
as Greg pointed out at the beginning of his talk, the difference can be
very counterintuitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second talk that I recommend is
&lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/"&gt;Jake VanderPlas&lt;/a&gt;'s talk about Frequentism and
Bayesianism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/KhAUfqhLakw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won't summarize this talk, as Jake has done a much better job in his blog
(parts
&lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/03/11/frequentism-and-bayesianism-a-practical-intro/"&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/06/frequentism-and-bayesianism-2-when-results-differ/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/12/frequentism-and-bayesianism-3-confidence-credibility/"&gt;three&lt;/a&gt;,
and
&lt;a href="http://jakevdp.github.io/blog/2014/06/14/frequentism-and-bayesianism-4-bayesian-in-python/"&gt;four&lt;/a&gt;). The
best thing is to just watch the talk.  I will just point out that before the
talk, I did not really understand the difference, not being a statistician or
someone who works with statistics regularly, and having seen the talk, I now
feel that I do.  It's a controversial topic, and if you care about the matter,
you should know that Jake is a strong Bayesian, although I felt that he gave
both sides a fair exposition&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, all talks I saw at the conference were good. But those two I felt were
the best. I should also mention here that I myself gave a talk on Conda (more
on that later).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the talks are only a part of any conference. The best part of SciPy
is the gathering of the community. Each year I meet more new people, as well
as talk with people I already know, but don't get to see outside of SciPy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, the biggest part of the interactions this year were on Conda and
packaging.  The background is that I have been working full time for Continuum
since January, and I had interned last summer, working primarily on the Conda
package manager and Anaconda, the Python distribution.  This year, some of the
biggest buzz was about Conda.  Just like everyone was talking about the
IPython Notebook last year and how it has solved the fundamental problems of
sharing and presenting data analysis, this year, everyone thanked me for my
work on Conda and how it has basically solved the packaging problem, the
ubiquitous problem in Python since people started using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conda: The Packaging Problem Solved&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the talk I gave on Conda:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/UaIvrDWrIWM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made the claim in my talk that Conda has solved the packaging problem, and
the general feel from people I talked to who are using Conda is that it has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this slide from my presentation summarizes why Conda solves the
packaging problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://asmeurer.github.io/galleries/conda_scipy2014_slide.png" width="500"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most amazing thing about the scientific Python community, and one of the
things that I think really sets it apart from other Python communities, is the
use of Python and other languages, such as C, C++, Fortran, R, or Julia.  No
one language is enough to get the job done for serious scientific work.  The
brokenness of Python packaging has been that it has focused too much on Python
specific tools and processes.  The distutils/setuptools/pip/virtualenv stack
works great if your code begins and ends with Python.  Where it falls over is
when you want to link against a C library, compile some Fortran or Cython
code, and communicate with other languages like R and Julia.  By being a
system level package manager, which is fundamentally Python agnostic, Conda is
able to deal with all packages equally, whether that package be a Python
package, a C extension which other packages link against, or Python itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By being truly cross-platform and user installable, Conda is able to reach the
maximal number of users, especially those who have historically been hit by
the packaging problem the hardest, namely, those who are on Windows or those
who do not have admin rights to install necessary tools to install the
packages they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Conda installs binaries, not source packages, and its metadata is
entirely static (you do not need to execute arbitrary Python code to capture
the metadata of a package).  These two things remove two of the largest
sources of issues with the existing Python packaging tools, such as compiler
errors, and nonuniformity in metadata standards (there seem to be as many
different ways of writing &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt; as there are packages on PyPI).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conda opens up its ecosystem to anybody by making it easy for people to build
their own Conda packages using reproducible Conda recipes.  And
&lt;a href="https://binstar.org/"&gt;Binstar&lt;/a&gt; makes it easy to share those packages.  I'm
very excited about Binstar, as I think it does for packaging what GitHub has
done for open source, i.e., distributes and democratizes it. There are
challenges on how to deal with this, of course. As with any distributed
democratized system, Binstar can be a wild west of packages.  Continuum is
thinking about ways to manage this complexity, while still reaping the
benefits it provides. If you have any thoughts on things that can be done, let
me know in the comments section below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Sprints&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conference ended with two days of sprints. I mainly helped people with
Conda packaging.  A key thing for me is that I worked with Aron Ahmadia so
that HashDist can generate Conda packages. HashDist is a package compiling
framework that makes it easy to have completely reproducible builds by hashing
all the information that was used to compile a package, and recompiling when
any of that information changes. You can learn more about HashDist by watching
Aron's talk from the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/wviHkzk0AkY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am now convinced that HashDist is a good solution for people who still want
the control of compiling their own packages. If HashDist is able to produce
Conda packages, then you can gain the benefits of both worlds: Conda's
powerful package management and environment notion, with HashDist's modular
and reproducible package building framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The organizers of SciPy did an excellent job this year.  The video crew did
something which I have not seen before, which is that they uploaded the videos
of the talks on the same day that the talks were held. My talk, which was held
right before lunch, was uploaded before the last talk of the day.  Something
that I saw come out of this is that people not attending the conference were
able to watch the talks and take part of the conversation with the conference
attendees, via Twitter and other social media, or by joining the sprints after
the conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extended three days of talks really took their toll on me. The conference
starts early enough in the morning and the social events after go so late in
the evening that each day of the conference I become a little more sleep
deprived. Usually by two days of tutorials and two days of talks I have hit my
limit, and this year, I really had a hard time making it through that fifth
day. Fortunately I can sleep in a little bit for the sprints, as it's not a
big deal if you miss the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year the conference organizers made a push for diversity, and it
shows. There were noticeably more women at the conference this year, and not
just insomuch as there were more people at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- LocalWords:  Gede Obinna Nwanna iframe src frameborder allowfullscreen -
--&gt;

&lt;!--  LocalWords:  - VanderPlas 's PyDy 's img Ahmadia
 --&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>http://asmeurer.github.io/posts/scipy-2014/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 16:52:27 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moving to GitHub pages with Nikola</title><link>http://asmeurer.github.io/posts/moving-to-github-pages-with-nikola/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So I've finally decided to move my blog from Wordpress to GitHub pages.  I
highly recommend it if you are technically skilled enough to do it. I was
getting pretty annoyed at Wordpress. It forces you to write your posts in
html (or else using their WYSIWYG editor), the wordpress.com is locked down,
so you can't add any Javascript, their math is stuck in the past rendering png
instead of using MathJax. The list goes on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With GitHub pages, I can write my posts in Markdown, and I have full control
over everything. And there is no lock in. If I decide I don't like the
software that is generating the posts, I can easily move to something else,
since the post content itself is all Markdown (or the occasional rst or
IPython notebook if I want to do something that Markdown doesn't support). I
can use MathJax for math (like \( e^{i\pi} + 1 = 0 \)). Wordpress.com
doesn't let you install abtirary Javascript on your blog, so you can't do
things like install MathJax or enable some cool sidebar thing (like a Twitter
feed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Setting up GitHub Pages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you need to set up GitHub pages. This is a bit confusing, because there
are actually two kinds of GitHub pages, user pages and project pages. User
pages are if you have a repo named &lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;.com&lt;/code&gt;). The pages
are served from the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For project pages, you add a &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch to any one of your projects,
and GitHub hosts the content automatically at
&lt;code&gt;username.github.io/projectname&lt;/code&gt;. I originally had my blog content at
&lt;code&gt;asmeurer.github.io&lt;/code&gt;, but I didn't like that I had to do everything in master,
both the generated and original content. So instead I created a repo called
&lt;code&gt;blog&lt;/code&gt;. I have my content in the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch and the generated pages in
the &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch (more on this later). At my
&lt;a href="https://github.com/asmeurer/asmeurer.github.com"&gt;&lt;code&gt;asmeurer.github.com&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; repo,
I just have for now a basic redirect to the blog. In the future, I may want to
put additional, non-blog content on the website, and it would go there (or in
a separate project repo with its own &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Nikola&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had initially planned on using
&lt;a href="http://blog.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;. However, I got stalled on the
Wordpress import. I like that Pelican is written in Python, but I was not too
keen on their abrasive
&lt;a href="https://github.com/getpelican/pelican/blob/master/LICENSE"&gt;license&lt;/a&gt;. Frankly,
I shouldn't say too many bad things about Pelican because I never really tried
that hard with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have decided to try &lt;a href="http://getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; instead. It's also
written in Python. It has a very nice
&lt;a href="https://github.com/getnikola/nikola/blob/master/LICENSE.txt"&gt;license&lt;/a&gt;. I like
the philosophy of the &lt;a href="http://getnikola.com/handbook.html"&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;DON'T READ THIS MANUAL. IF YOU NEED TO READ IT I FAILED, JUST USE THE THING.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've also discovered that the
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/nikola-discuss"&gt;Nikola community&lt;/a&gt; is
&lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; nice. And of course, even if Nikola ends up not being for me, it will
be easy to switch, because my actual content is just some Markdown files that
I own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Getting started&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting started with Nikola is pretty easy. First, you need to install it. It
has a &lt;em&gt;ton&lt;/em&gt; of dependencies (fortunately all Python, so it won't be that
hard). In addition to the ones in the requirements.txt, you should also
install &lt;code&gt;markdown&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;webassets&lt;/code&gt;. While using &lt;code&gt;nikola&lt;/code&gt;, it will tell you if
you don't have something installed that you should, so if you see that, just
install what it tells you to.  If you use &lt;code&gt;conda&lt;/code&gt; and Mac OS X, I have
uploaded all the dependencies to my &lt;a href="https://binstar.org/asmeurer/"&gt;Binstar&lt;/a&gt;,
so you can just &lt;code&gt;conda install -c asmeurer nikola&lt;/code&gt;. Oh and don't worry, Nikola
and its dependencies fully support Python 3 (I wouldn't be using it if they
didn't).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you just run the commands from
http://getnikola.com/handbook.html#all-you-need-to-know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that doesn't tell you is that after you init the site, you should
walk through &lt;code&gt;conf.py&lt;/code&gt; and change the settings to your liking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another trick not there is that you can add&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;eval&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"`nikola tabcompletion`"&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;to your Bash profile to get tab completion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Tricks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some useful tricks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable MathJax, you have to type &lt;code&gt;mathjax&lt;/code&gt; in a line by itself in the
metadata file. There are some bugs right now, but ideally you could do inline
math with &lt;code&gt;$math$&lt;/code&gt; and display math with &lt;code&gt;$$math$$&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;$math$&lt;/code&gt; doesn't work
currently, but you can do &lt;code&gt;\\(math\\)&lt;/code&gt; (both &lt;code&gt;\&lt;/code&gt;s are required, although this
is likely a bug). You can do &lt;code&gt;\\[math\\]&lt;/code&gt; for display math.  Here are some
examples. Inline: \( \sin ^2{x} + \cos^2{x} = 1\). Display: $$ e^{i\pi} + 1 = 0 .$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your one-stop command when blogging is &lt;code&gt;nikola auto&lt;/code&gt;. This requires
  &lt;code&gt;livereload&lt;/code&gt;. This will serve the blog on localhost, and automatically
  rebuild it when any change is made (and I really mean &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; change: it can
  even detect when you change Nikola itself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have the following in my conf.py to deploy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DEPLOY_COMMANDS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"git checkout gh-pages"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"rsync -rPv --delete-after --exclude old_blog --exclude .git --exclude .gitignore --exclude cache/ --exclude .doit.db.db output/ ."&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"git add -A"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"git commit -a -m 'Updating blog content'"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"git push"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s"&gt;"git checkout master"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;WARNING: These commands are dangerous. If you don't properly exclude things
like &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt;, you will wipe your entire git history. I &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend
committing everything and pushing to GitHub before deploying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;_site&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;pyc&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;DS_Store&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;doit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;db&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;db&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;cache&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;for your &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite what it says on the Nikola page, be sure to read the docs, because
there are a lot of cool features you won't know about unless you read about
them. Also be sure to read through &lt;code&gt;conf.py&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wordpress import&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is something that I am still figuring out. You can see the progress at
  &lt;a href="http://asmeurer.github.io/blog/old_blog"&gt;http://asmeurer.github.io/blog/old_blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importing from Wordpress is pretty easy actually (at least in theory). First
you need to go to the Wordpress site dashboard and go to "Export" from the
"Tools" menu. From here you can download an XML file with all your
content. Then just do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;nikola&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;import_wordpress&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;export_file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;xml&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Note that the current version of Nikola as of this writing (6.3.0) doesn't do
this right, so you'll need to use the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/getnikola/nikola"&gt;git master&lt;/a&gt;. There are some issues with
the import, since Wordpress has its own markup that it doesn't know everything
about, so you may need to go in and fix things. Or report them as bugs to
Nikola and reimport when they are fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll need to go through the posts and make sure that they are rendered
correctly (this is one reason I haven't finished doing it yet).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For comments, you first need to create a Disqus account, and enable it in your
conf.py. You should then upload the xml file that you exported from Wordpress
to Disqus. At this point, the comments should just work, because Nikola sets
the Disqus url for the imported comments to the old Wordpress url (look at the
Disqus section of one of the built pages).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how to automatically backlink from Wordpress back to
Nikola. Maybe I should just automatically generate some links and paste them
in manually.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>mathjax</category><guid>http://asmeurer.github.io/posts/moving-to-github-pages-with-nikola/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2014 23:19:18 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>