<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Aaron Meurer's Blog</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/</link><description>My blog</description><atom:link href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2019 03:35:15 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>GitHub Cuts</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-cuts/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;GitHub recently announced its &lt;a href="https://blog.github.com/2018-08-28-announcing-paper-cuts/"&gt;paper cuts
initiative&lt;/a&gt; to fix
minor issues that make things more difficult for GitHub users. As someone who
spends most of his day on &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt;, this initiative is
great, as these small cuts can quickly add up to a painful experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative has already made some great fixes, such as &lt;a href="https://blog.github.com/changelog/2018-07-31-unselectable-diff-markers/"&gt;making the diff
markers
unselectable&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="https://blog.github.com/changelog/2018-10-08-issue-and-pull-request-hovercards/"&gt;hovercards&lt;/a&gt;.
Small changes like these are usually quite easy for GitHub to do, but they
make a huge difference to those of use who use GitHub every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/1034528642389266432"&gt;recently asked&lt;/a&gt;
how these cuts could be reported to GitHub for fixing, but got no response. So
I am writing this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be very clear: I think that on the whole GitHub is great and they are doing
a great job. And it's still better than the alternatives (to put things in
perspective, I recently spent &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/1029158262069899266"&gt;half an
hour&lt;/a&gt; trying to
figure out how to change my password in BitBucket, and GitLab can't even keep
me logged in between sessions). GitHub has and continues to revolutionize the
open source ecosystem, and is still the best place to host an open source
project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since GitHub did
&lt;a href="https://blog.github.com/2018-08-28-announcing-paper-cuts/"&gt;ask&lt;/a&gt; what sorts of
changes they want to see, I'm providing a list. In this post I'm trying to
only ask about things that are small changes (though I realize many won't be
as easy to fix as they may appear from the outside, and I readily admit that I
am not a web developer).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just the things that have bothered me, personally. Other people use
GitHub differently and no doubt have their own pain points. For instance, I
have no suggestions about the project boards feature of GitHub because I don't
use it. If you are also a GitHub user and have your own pain points feel free
to use the comment box below (though I have no idea if GitHub will actually
see them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work for GitHub and have any questions, feel free to comment below, or
&lt;a href="mailto:asmeurer@gmail.com"&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow anyone to add labels to issues.&lt;/strong&gt; At the very least, allow the
person who opened the issue to add labels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new issue transfer ability is great, but please &lt;strong&gt;make it require only
push access, not admin access.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remove the automatic hiding of comments when there are too many.&lt;/strong&gt; I
understand this is done for technical reasons, but it breaks
Cmd-F/scrolling through the page to find comments. Often I go to an issue
trying to find an old comment and can't because buried in the comments is a
button I have to press to actually show the comment (it's even worse when
you have to find and press the button multiple times).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better indication for cross-referenced pull requests.&lt;/strong&gt; I really don't
know how to fix this, only that it is a problem. It happens all the time
that a new contributor comes to a SymPy issue and asks if it has been
worked on yet. They generally do not seem to notice the cross-referenced
pull requests in the list.
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues/14943"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is an example of what
I'm talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Indicate better if a cross-referenced pull request would close an
issue.&lt;/strong&gt; Preferably with text, not just an icon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTML pull request/issue templates.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't know if this counts as a
"cut", as it isn't a simple fix. Right now, many projects use pull
requests/new issue templates, but it is not very user friendly. The problem
is that the whole thing is done in plain text, often with the template text
as an HTML comment to prevent it from appearing in the final issue text.
Even for me, I often find this quite difficult to read through, but for new
contributors, we often find that they don't read it at all. Sure there's no
way to force people to read, but if we could instead create a very simple
HTML form for people to fill out, it would be much more friendly, even to
experienced people like myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fix the back button in Chrome.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't know if this is something that
GitHub can fix, and I also do not know how things work in other browsers. I
use Chrome on macOS. Often, when I click the "back" button and it takes me
back to an issue page, the contents of the page are out-of-date (the newest
comments or commits do not appear). It's often even more out-of-date than
it was when I left the page. I have to reload the page to get the latest
content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Markdown formatting in issue titles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show people's names next to comments as "Real Name (@username)".&lt;/strong&gt; In
general, GitHub should be emphasizing people's display names rather than
their usernames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember my selection for the "sort" setting in the issues list.&lt;/strong&gt; I'd
love to have issues/pull requests sort by "most recently updated" by
default, so that I don't miss updates to old issues/pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make advanced search filters more accessible.&lt;/strong&gt; They should autofill,
similar to how Gmail or even GitLab search works (yes, please steal all
the good ideas from GitLab; they already stole all their good ideas from
you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tone down the reaction emojis.&lt;/strong&gt; Maybe this ship has sailed, but
reaction emojis are way too unprofessional for some projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copy/paste text as Markdown.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, copying "&lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;" and
pasting it into the comment box would paste &lt;code&gt;**bold**&lt;/code&gt;. Another idea that
you can steal from GitLab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strike out #12345 issue links when the issue/PR is closed/merged&lt;/strong&gt;
(like &lt;strike&gt;#12345&lt;/strike&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pull requests&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="15"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a button that automatically merges a pull request as soon as all the
CI checks pass.&lt;/strong&gt; Any additional commits pushed to the branch in the
interim would cancel it, and it should also be cancellable by someone else
with push access or the PR author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add some way to disable the automatic hiding of large diffs.&lt;/strong&gt; This
breaks Cmd-F on the page, and makes it harder to scroll through the pull
request to find what you are looking for (typically the most important
changes are the ones that are hidden!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Include all issue/PR authors in the authors search on the pull request
list page.&lt;/strong&gt; Right now it only lists people with push access. But I
generally can't remember people's GitHub usernames, and autofilling based
on all authors would be very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Better contextual guesses for issue autofilling (after typing &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/strong&gt;
For instance, if an issue has already been referenced or cross-referenced,
it should appear near the top of the list. We have almost &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/issues"&gt;3000 open
issues&lt;/a&gt; in SymPy, and the current
issue numbers are 5-digits long, so referencing an issue purely by number
is very error prone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Auto-update edited comments.&lt;/strong&gt; Context: SymPy uses a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy-bot"&gt;bot&lt;/a&gt; that comments on every pull
request, requiring a release notes entry to be added to the description.
This works quite well, but to prevent the bot from spamming, we have it
comment only once, and edit its comment on any further checks. However,
these edits do not automatically update, so people have to manually reload
the page to see them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't hide full commit messages by default in the commits view.&lt;/strong&gt; It
would be better to encourage people to write good commit messages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make issue cross-references in pull request titles work.&lt;/strong&gt; I'd rather
people didn't put issue numbers in pull request titles but they do it
anyway, so it would be nice if they actually worked as links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow me to comment on lines that aren't visible by default.&lt;/strong&gt; That is,
lines that you have to click the "expand" icon above or below the line
numbers to access. As an example, this can be useful to point out a line
that should have been changed but wasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copying code from a diff that includes lines that aren't visible by
default includes an extra space to the left for those lines.&lt;/strong&gt; This is a
straight up bug. Probably fixing the previous point would also fix this :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make searches include text from the pull request diff.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When a diff indents a line color the whitespace to the left of the
line.&lt;/strong&gt; (see
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/740611970714480640"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pull requests can show commits that are already in master.&lt;/strong&gt; For
example, if someone makes pull request B based off of pull request A and
then A gets merged, B will still show the commits from A. This has been a
bug forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the "jump to file or symbol" popdown collapsible.&lt;/strong&gt; Specifically
what I mean is I want to be able to show just the files, without any
symbols. For large pull requests, it is very difficult to use this popdown
if there are hundreds of symbols. I typically want to just jump to a
specific file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The status check on the favicon goes away when you switch to the diff
tab.&lt;/strong&gt; Kudos to Marius Gedminas for &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mgedmin/status/1058381090694553601"&gt;pointing this
out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/15280#issuecomment-426795606"&gt;Apparently&lt;/a&gt;
status checks that use the GitHub Apps API are forced to link into the
checks tab.&lt;/strong&gt; The checks tab is useless if no information is actually
published to it. It would be better if it could link straight to the
external site, like is done with oauth integrations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make it easier to copy someone's username from the pull request page.&lt;/strong&gt;
I generally do this to &lt;code&gt;git remote add&lt;/code&gt; them (using
&lt;a href="https://github.com/github/hub"&gt;hub&lt;/a&gt;). If I try to select their username
from a comment, it's a link, which makes it hard to select. I generally
copy it from the blue text at the top "&lt;em&gt;user&lt;/em&gt; wants to merge &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; commits
from &lt;code&gt;sympy:master&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;code&gt;user:branch&lt;/code&gt;". If it were easier to select
"user" or "branch" from that box (say, by double clicking), that would be
helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change the "resolve conversation" UI.&lt;/strong&gt; I keep pressing it on accident
because it's where I expect the "new comment" button to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Reviews&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote a &lt;a href="https://www.asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-reviews-gripes/"&gt;whole
post&lt;/a&gt; about the
reviews feature when it came out. Not much has changed since then (actually,
it has gotten worse). In short, the feature doesn't work like I would like it
too, and I find the default behavior of deferred comments to be extremely
detrimental. If there were a way to completely disable reviews (for myself, I
don't care about other people using the feature), I would.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my blog post for full details on why I think the reviews feature is broken
and actually makes things worse, not better than before. I've summarized a few
things that could change below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="32"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make reviews non-deferred by default.&lt;/strong&gt; This is the biggest thing. If I
had to pick only a single item on this page to be changed, it would be
this. The issue is if I start a review and walk away from it, but forget
to "finalize" it with a review status, the review is never actually seen
by anyone. The simplest way to fix this would be to simply make partial
reviews public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make Cmd-Enter default to immediate comment.&lt;/strong&gt; Barring the above change,
Cmd-Enter on a pull request line comment should default to immediate
comment, not deferred (review) comment. The problem with the
Cmd-Shift-Enter shortcut is that it is inconsistent: on a normal comment,
it closes the pull request, and on a reply comment, it does nothing. I
shouldn't have to check what "comment context" I am in to figure out what
keyboard shortcut to use. The worst part is if you accidentally start a
review, it's a pain in the ass to undo that and just post a normal
comment. The simplest way to fix this would be to swap the current meaning
of Cmd-Enter and Cmd-Shift-Enter for line comments (and no, this wouldn't
be a backwards incompatible change, it would be a regression fix;
Cmd-Enter &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; to do the right thing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow reviewing your own pull request.&lt;/strong&gt; There's no reason to disallow
this, and it would often be quite useful to, for instance, mark a work in
progress PR as such with a "request changes" review. Obviously
self-reviews would be excluded from any required reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unhide the reviews box.&lt;/strong&gt; It should just be the same box as the comment
box, unstead of buried on the diff tab (see my &lt;a href="https://www.asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-reviews-gripes/"&gt;blog
post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show review status in the pull request list as a red X or green check.&lt;/strong&gt;
This would make it easier to see which pull requests have reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow new commits to invalidate reviews.&lt;/strong&gt; That way they work the same
way as any other status check. (I see that this is now an option for
required reviews, which is new since my original blog post, but it still
doesn't affect the status as reported on the pull requests list).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow requiring zero negative reviews to merge (but not necessarily any
positive reviews)&lt;/strong&gt;. Requiring a positive review is pointless. The person
merging can just add one real quick before they merge, but it is
unnecessary extra work. On the other hand allowing people with push access
to block a merge with a negative review would be very useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Web editor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="39"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The web editor seems to have a search function, but I can't get it to
actually work.&lt;/strong&gt; Half the time Cmd-F pops open the browser search, which
doesn't find text that isn't on screen. And when I press Cmd-G to actually
do the search, it doesn't work (and there are no buttons to perform the
search either).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add basic syntax testing in the web editor for common languages to catch
basic mistakes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mobile site&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="41"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Please make the mobile site work with iOS 10.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't see any reason
why simple things like buttons (like the merge button or the comment
button) shouldn't work on a slightly older browser. No, I am not a web
developer, but I do use my phone a lot and I've noticed that literally
every other website works just fine on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a way to disable the mobile site permanently.&lt;/strong&gt; For the most part,
the mobile site is useless (see below). If you aren't going to put full
development effort into it, allow me to disable it permanently so that
every time I visit &lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; on my phone it goes to
the desktop site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing as how the site (mobile or not) is almost completely unusable on every
mobile device I own, it's hard to list other things here, but based on back
when it actually worked, these are some of the things that annoyed me the
most. Basically, I have found that virtually every time I go to GitHub to do
anything on mobile, I have to switch to desktop mode to actually do what I
want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My apologies if any of these actually work now: as I said,
&lt;a href="https://github.com"&gt;github.com&lt;/a&gt; doesn't actually work at all on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="43"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cannot search issues on mobile.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cannot make a line comment that &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; a review on mobile.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cannot view lines beyond the default diff in pull requests on mobile.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show more than 2 lines of the README and 0 lines of the code by default
on project pages.&lt;/strong&gt; Yes mobile screens are small but it's also not hard to
scroll on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Support Jupyter notebook rendering on mobile.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Files view&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="48"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GitHub needs a better default color theme for syntax highlighting.&lt;/strong&gt;
Most of the colors are very similar to one another and hard to
differentiate. Also things like strings are black, even though one of the
most useful aspects of syntax highlighting generally is to indicate
whether something is in a string or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add MathJax support to markdown files.&lt;/strong&gt; This would be amazingly useful
for SymPy, as well as many scientific software projects. Right now if you
want this you have to use a Jupyter notebook. MathJax support in
issue/pull request comments would be awesome as well, though I'm not
holding out for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add "display source" button for markdown, ReST, etc.&lt;/strong&gt; I mean the button
that is already there for Jupyter notebooks. Right now you have to view
markdown and ReST files "raw" or edit the file to see their source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a link to the pull request in the blame view.&lt;/strong&gt; Usually I want to
find the pull request that produced a change, not just the commit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wiki&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="52"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The wikis used to support LaTeX math with MathJax. It would be great if
this were re-added.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The ability to set push permissions for the wiki separately from the
repo it is attached to, or otherwise create an oauth token that can only
push to the wiki would be useful.&lt;/strong&gt; Context: for SymPy, we use a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy-bot"&gt;bot&lt;/a&gt; that automatically updates our
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/Release-Notes"&gt;release notes&lt;/a&gt; on our
wiki. It works quite well, but the only way it can push to the wiki is if
we give it push access to the full repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Notification emails&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="54"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don't clobber special emails/email headers.&lt;/strong&gt; GitHub adds special emails
like &lt;a href="mailto:author@noreply.github.com"&gt;author@noreply.github.com&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="mailto:mention@noreply.github.com"&gt;mention@noreply.github.com&lt;/a&gt; to email
notifications based on how the notification was triggered. This is useful,
as I can create an email filter for
&lt;a href="mailto:author@noreply.github.com"&gt;author@noreply.github.com&lt;/a&gt; for
notifications on issues and pull requests created by me. The bad news is,
&lt;a href="mailto:mention@noreply.github.com"&gt;mention@noreply.github.com&lt;/a&gt;, which is
added when I am @mentioned, clobbers
&lt;a href="mailto:author@noreply.github.com"&gt;author@noreply.github.com&lt;/a&gt;, so that it
doesn't appear anymore. In other words, as soon as someone @mentions me in
one of my issues, I become &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; likely to see it, because it no longer
gets my label (I get @mentioned on &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of issues and don't have the
ability to read all of my notification emails). Ditto for the
&lt;code&gt;X-GitHub-Reason&lt;/code&gt; email headers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Readd the "view issue" links in Gmail.&lt;/strong&gt; (I forgot what these are
called). GitHub notification emails used to have these useful "view issue"
buttons that showed up on the right in the email list in Gmail, but they
were removed for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;API&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="56"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make the requests in the API docs actually return what they show in the
docs.&lt;/strong&gt; This means the &lt;a href="https://github.com/octocat/Hello-World/"&gt;example
repo&lt;/a&gt; should have actual example
issues corresponding to what is shown in the docs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow giving deploy key access to just one branch.&lt;/strong&gt; That way I can have
a deploy key for &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; and minimize the attack surface that the
existence of that key produces. I think everyone would agree that more
fine-grained permissions throughout the API would be nice, but this is one
that would benefit me personally, specifically for my project
&lt;a href="https://drdoctr.github.io/"&gt;doctr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub pages is one of the best features of GitHub, and in fact, this very
blog is hosted on it. Very few complaints here, because for the most part, it
"just works".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol start="58"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/831962312122761216"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Moar themes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Also it's awesome that you can use any GitHub repo as a theme now, but it
turns out most random themes you find around GitHub don't actually work
very well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The steps to add HTTPS to an existing GitHub pages custom domain are a
bit confusing.&lt;/strong&gt;. This took us a while to figure out for
&lt;a href="https://sympy.org"&gt;sympy.org&lt;/a&gt;. To get things to work, you have to trigger
GitHub to issue a cert for the domain. But the UI to issue the cert is to
paste the domain into the box. So if the domain is already there but it
doesn't work, you have to re-enter it. Also if you want both www and the
apex domain to be HTTPS you have to enter them both in the box to trigger
GitHub to issue a cert. This is primarily a UX issue. See
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy.github.com/issues/105#issuecomment-415899934"&gt;https://github.com/sympy/sympy.github.com/issues/105#issuecomment-415899934&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="60"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automatically protected branches make the branch difficult to delete
when you are done with it.&lt;/strong&gt; My use-case is to create a branch for a
release, which I want to protect, but I also want to delete the branch
once it is merged. I can protect the branch automatically pretty easily,
but then I have to go and delete the protection rule when it's merged to
delete it. There are several ways this could be fixed. For instance, you
could add a rule to allow protected branches to be deleted if they are
up-to-date with default branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add a way to disable the ability for non-admins to create new branches
on a repo.&lt;/strong&gt; We want all of our pull requests to come from forks. Branches
in the repo just create confusion, for instance, they appear whenever
someone clones the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related to the previous point, make pull request reverts come from
forks.&lt;/strong&gt; Right now when someone uses the revert pull request button, it
creates a new branch in the same repo, but it would be better if the
branch were made in the person's fork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow me to enable branch protection by default for new repos.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow me to enable branch protection by default on new branches.&lt;/strong&gt; This
is more important than the previous one because of the feature that lets
people push to your branch on a pull request (which is a great feature by
the way).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clicking a team name in the settings should default to the "members"
tab.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't understand why GitHub has a non-open "discussions" feature,
but I find it to be completely useless, and generally see such things as
harmful for open source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Suggest people to add push access to.&lt;/strong&gt; I don't necessarily mean
passively (though that could be interesting too), but I mean in the page
to add someone, it would be nice if the popup suggested or indicated which
people had contributed the project before, since just searching for a name
searches all of GitHub, and I don't want to accidentally give access to
the wrong person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Profiles&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="67"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stop trying to make profile pages look "cute" with randomly highlighted
pull requests.&lt;/strong&gt; GitHub should have learned by now that profile pages
matter a lot (whether people want them to or not), and there can be
unintended consequences to the things that are put on them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explain what the axes actually mean in the new "activity overview".&lt;/strong&gt;
I'm referring to
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/1033141923630874624"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; (it's
still in beta and you have to manually enable it on your profile page).
Personally I'm leaving the feature off because I don't like being
metricized/gamified, but if you're going to have it, at least include some
transparency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Releases&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="69"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow hiding the "source code (zip)" and "source code (tar.gz)" files in
a release.&lt;/strong&gt; We upload our actual release files (generated by &lt;code&gt;setup.py&lt;/code&gt;)
to the GitHub release. We want people to download those, not snapshots of
the repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol start="70"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The repository search function doesn't support partial matches.&lt;/strong&gt; This
is annoying for &lt;a href="https://github.com/conda-forge/"&gt;conda-forge&lt;/a&gt;. For
instance, if I &lt;a href="https://github.com/conda-forge/?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=png&amp;amp;type=&amp;amp;language="&gt;search for
"png"&lt;/a&gt;
it doesn't show the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/conda-forge/libpng-feedstock"&gt;libpng-feedstock&lt;/a&gt; repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Show commit history as a graph.&lt;/strong&gt; Like &lt;code&gt;git log --graph&lt;/code&gt;. This would go
a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; way to helping new users understand git. When I first started
with git, understanding the history as a graph was a major part of me
finally grokking how it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bring back the old "fork" UI.&lt;/strong&gt; The one that just had icons for all the
repos, and the icons didn't go away or become harder to find if you
already had a fork. Some of us use the "fork" button to go to our
pre-existing forks, not just to perform a fork action. This was recently
changed and now it's better than it was, but I still don't see why
existing forks need to be harder to find, visually, than nonexisting ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Provide a more official way to request fixes to these cuts.&lt;/strong&gt; I often
ask on Twitter, but get no response. Preferably something public so that
others could vote on them (but I understand if you don't want too much
bikeshedding).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-cuts/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2018 22:54:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Automatically deploying this blog to GitHub Pages with Travis CI</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/automatically-deploying-this-blog-to-github-pages-with-travis-ci/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This blog is now &lt;a href="http://travis-ci.org/asmeurer/blog"&gt;deployed to GitHub pages automatically&lt;/a&gt; from Travis CI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I've outlined in the &lt;a href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/automatically-deploying-this-blog-to-github-pages-with-travis-ci/moving-to-github-pages-with-nikola/"&gt;past&lt;/a&gt;, this
website is built with the &lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/"&gt;Nikola&lt;/a&gt; static blogging
engine. I really like Nikola because it uses Python, has lots of nice
extensions, and
is
&lt;a href="https://github.com/getnikola/nikola/blob/master/LICENSE.txt"&gt;sanely licensed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, it is a static site generator, meaning I write my posts in
Markdown, and Nikola generates the site as static web content ("static" means no web server
is required to run the site). This means that the site can be hosted for free
on &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com/"&gt;GitHub pages&lt;/a&gt;. This is how this site has been
hosted since I started it. I have
a &lt;a href="http://github.com/asmeurer/blog"&gt;GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt; for the site, and the content
itself is deployed to
the &lt;a href="https://github.com/asmeurer/blog/tree/gh-pages"&gt;gh-pages&lt;/a&gt; branch of the
repo. But until now, the deployment has happened only manually with the
&lt;code&gt;nikola github_deploy&lt;/code&gt; command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A much better way is to deploy automatically using Travis CI. That way, I do
not need to run any software on my computer to deploy the blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps outlined here will work for any static site generator. They assume
you already have one set up and hosted on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 1: Create a .travis.yml file&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; file like the one below&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-yaml"&gt;sudo: false
language: python

python:
  - 3.6

install:
  - pip install "Nikola[extras]" doctr

script:
  - set -e
  - nikola build
  - doctr deploy . --built-docs output/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you use a different static site generator, replace &lt;code&gt;nikola&lt;/code&gt; with that
site generator's command.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you have Nikola configured to output to a different directory, or use a
different static site generator, replace &lt;code&gt;--built-docs output/&lt;/code&gt; with the
directory where the site is built.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add any extra packages you need to build your site to the &lt;code&gt;pip install&lt;/code&gt;
command. For instance, I use the &lt;code&gt;commonmark&lt;/code&gt; extension for Nikola, so I
need to install &lt;code&gt;commonmark&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;code&gt;set -e&lt;/code&gt; line is important. It will prevent the blog from being deployed
if the build fails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then go to &lt;a href="http://www.asmeurer.com/blog/"&gt;https://travis-ci.org/profile/&lt;/a&gt; and enable Travis for your blog
repo.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Step 2: Run doctr&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key here is &lt;a href="https://drdoctr.github.io/doctr/"&gt;doctr&lt;/a&gt;, a tool I wrote with
&lt;a href="https://github.com/gforsyth"&gt;Gil Forsyth&lt;/a&gt; that makes deploying anything from
Travis CI to GitHub Pages a breeze. It automatically handles creating and
encrypting a deploy SSH key for GitHub, and the syncing of files to the
&lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First install doctr.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;code&gt;doctr&lt;/code&gt; requires
Python 3.5+, so you'll need that. You can install it with conda:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;conda install -c conda-forge doctr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or if you don't use conda, with pip&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;pip install doctr
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then run this command in your blog repo:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash"&gt;doctr configure
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will ask you for your GitHub username and password,
and for the name of the repo you are deploying from and to (for instance, for
my blog, I entered &lt;code&gt;asmeurer/blog&lt;/code&gt;). The output will look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- http seems to give the least amount of highlighting. text is --&gt;
&lt;!-- supposed to work, but doesn't render correctly. --&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-http"&gt;$ doctr configure
What is your GitHub username? asmeurer
Enter the GitHub password for asmeurer:
A two-factor authentication code is required: app
Authentication code: 911451
What repo do you want to build the docs for (org/reponame, like 'drdoctr/doctr')? asmeurer/blog
What repo do you want to deploy the docs to? [asmeurer/blog] asmeurer/blog
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Your identification has been saved in github_deploy_key.
Your public key has been saved in github_deploy_key.pub.
The key fingerprint is:
SHA256:4cscEfJCy9DTUb3DnPNfvbBHod2bqH7LEqz4BvBEkqc doctr deploy key for asmeurer/blog
The key's randomart image is:
+---[RSA 4096]----+
|    ..+.oo..     |
|     *o*..  .    |
|      O.+  o o   |
|     E + o  B  . |
|      + S .  +o +|
|       = o o o.o+|
|        * . . =.=|
|       . o ..+ =.|
|        o..o+oo  |
+----[SHA256]-----+

The deploy key has been added for asmeurer/blog.

You can go to https://github.com/asmeurer/blog/settings/keys to revoke the deploy key.

================== You should now do the following ==================

1. Commit the file github_deploy_key.enc.

2. Add

    script:
      - set -e
      - # Command to build your docs
      - pip install doctr
      - doctr deploy &amp;lt;deploy_directory&amp;gt;

to the docs build of your .travis.yml.  The 'set -e' prevents doctr from
running when the docs build fails. Use the 'script' section so that if
doctr fails it causes the build to fail.

3. Put

    env:
      global:
        - secure: "Kf8DlqFuQz9ekJXpd3Q9sW5cs+CvaHpsXPSz0QmSZ01HlA4iOtdWVvUttDNb6VGyR6DcAkXlADRf/KzvAJvaqUVotETJ1LD2SegnPzgdz4t8zK21DhKt29PtqndeUocTBA6B3x6KnACdBx4enmZMTafTNRX82RMppwqxSMqO8mA="

in your .travis.yml.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Follow the steps at the end of the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commit the file &lt;code&gt;github_deploy_key.enc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You already have &lt;code&gt;doctr deploy&lt;/code&gt; in your &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; from step 1 above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Add the &lt;code&gt;env&lt;/code&gt; block to your &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This will let Travis CI decrypt
the SSH key used to deploy to &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;That's it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctr will now deploy your blog automatically. You may want to look at the
Travis build to make sure everything works. Note that &lt;code&gt;doctr&lt;/code&gt; only deploys
from &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; by default (see below). You may also want to look at the
other
&lt;a href="https://drdoctr.github.io/doctr/commandline.html#doctr-deploy"&gt;command line flags&lt;/a&gt; for
&lt;code&gt;doctr deploy&lt;/code&gt;, which let you do things such as to deploy to &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; for a
different repo than the one your blog is hosted on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recommend these steps over the ones in
the
&lt;a href="https://getnikola.com/blog/automating-nikola-rebuilds-with-travis-ci.html"&gt;Nikola manual&lt;/a&gt; because
doctr handles the SSH key generation for you, making things more secure. I
also found that the &lt;code&gt;nikola github_deploy&lt;/code&gt; command
was &lt;a href="https://github.com/getnikola/nikola/issues/2847"&gt;doing too much&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;code&gt;doctr&lt;/code&gt; handles syncing the built pages already anyway. Using &lt;code&gt;doctr&lt;/code&gt; is much
simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Extra stuff&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reverting a build&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a build goes wrong and you need to revert it, you'll need to use git to
revert the commit on your &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch. Unfortunately, GitHub doesn't
seem to have a way to revert commits in their web interface, so it has to be
done from the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Revoking the deploy key&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To revoke the deploy key generated by doctr, go your repo in GitHub, click on
"settings" and then "deploy keys". Do this if you decide to stop using this,
or if you feel the key may have been compromised. If you do this, the
deployment will stop until you run step 2 again to create a new key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Building the blog from branches&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also build your blog from branches, e.g., if you want to test things
out without deploying to the final repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will use the steps
outlined
&lt;a href="https://drdoctr.github.io/doctr/recipes.html#deploy-docs-from-any-branch"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Replace the line&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-yaml"&gt;  - doctr deploy . --built-docs output/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in your &lt;code&gt;.travis.yml&lt;/code&gt; with something like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-yaml"&gt;  - if [[ "${TRAVIS_BRANCH}" == "master" ]]; then
      doctr deploy . --built-docs output/;
    else
      doctr deploy "branch-$TRAVIS_BRANCH" --built-docs output/ --no-require-master;
    fi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will deploy your blog as normal from &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;, but from a branch it will
deploy to the &lt;code&gt;branch-&amp;lt;branchname&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; subdir. For instance, my blog is at
&lt;a href="http://www.asmeurer.com/blog/"&gt;http://www.asmeurer.com/blog/&lt;/a&gt;, and if I had a branch called &lt;code&gt;test&lt;/code&gt;, it would
deploy it to &lt;a href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/automatically-deploying-this-blog-to-github-pages-with-travis-ci/"&gt;http://www.asmeurer.com/blog/branch-test/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that it will not delete old branches for you from &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt;. You'll need
to do that manually once they are merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This only works for branches in the same repo. It is not possible to deploy
from a branch from pull request from a fork, for security purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Enable build cancellation in Travis&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go the Travis page for your blog and choose "settings" from the
hamburger menu, you can enable auto cancellation for branch builds. This will
make it so that if you push many changes in succession, only the most recent
one will get built. This makes the changes get built faster, and lets you
revert mistakes or typos without them ever actually being deployed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/automatically-deploying-this-blog-to-github-pages-with-travis-ci/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jun 2017 19:21:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>GitHub Reviews Gripes</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-reviews-gripes/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update: I want to keep the original post intact, but I'll post any feature
updates that GitHub makes here as they are released.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can now &lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2265-dismissing-reviews-on-pull-requests"&gt;dismiss a review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can
now
&lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2306-filter-pull-request-reviews-and-review-requests"&gt;filter the pull request list by review&lt;/a&gt;.
The review status of a PR also appears in the pull request list (albeit in
very tiny and easy to miss text).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;You can
now
&lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2330-restrict-review-dismissals-with-protected-branches"&gt;restrict review dismissals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub
&lt;a href="https://github.com/blog/2256-a-whole-new-github-universe-announcing-new-tools-forums-and-features"&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt; rolled
out a new feature on their pull requests called "Reviews". The feature is (in
theory), something that I've
been
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/sympy/KJwDwT_P6Lw/27ha6ipuBwAJ"&gt;asking for&lt;/a&gt;.
However, it really falls short in a big way, and I wanted to write down my
gripes with it, in the hopes that it spurs someone at GitHub to fix it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't know, GitHub has had, for some time, a feature called "pull
requests" ("PRs"), which lets you quite nicely show the diff and commit
differences between two branches before merging them. People can comment on
pull requests, or on individual lines in the diff. Once an administrator feels
that the pull request is "ready", they can click a button and have the branch
automatically merged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concept seems super simple
in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindsight_bias"&gt;retrospect&lt;/a&gt;, but this
feature completely revolutionized open source software development. It really
is the bread and butter of GitHub. I would argue that this one single feature
has made GitHub the (&lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt;) primary hosting site for open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from being an awesome idea, GitHub's trademark with pull requests, along
with their other features, has been absolute simplicity in implementation.
GitHub Reviews marks, by my estimation, the first major feature released by
GitHub that completely and utterly lacks in this execution of simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's look at what Reviews is. When the feature first came out, I had a hard
time figuring out how it even worked (the
poor
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/776125249712717824"&gt;release date docs&lt;/a&gt;
didn't help here either).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, at the bottom of a pull request, you now see this&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/reviews1.png" width="788"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clicking the "Add your review" button takes you to the diff page (first gripe:
why does it move you to the diff page?), and opens this dialog&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/reviews2.png" width="1020"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"OK", you might think, "this is simple enough. A review is just a special
comment box where I can approve or reject a pull request." (This is basically
the feature that I've been wanting, the ability to approve or reject pull
requests.) And if you thought that, you'd be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest way I can describe a review, having played with it, is that it is
a distinct method of commenting on pull requests and on lines of diffs of pull
requests. Distinct, that is, from the methods that &lt;strong&gt;already exist&lt;/strong&gt; in the
GitHub pull requests feature. That's right. There are now two ways to comment
on a pull request (or on a line in a pull request). There's the old way, which
involves typing text into the box at the bottom of the main pull request page
(or on a line, and then pressing "Add a single comment"), and the new way,
which involves clicking a special button at the top of the diff view (and the
diff view only) (or by clicking a line in the diff and
clicking "Start a review").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do these two ways of the extremely simple task of commenting differ from
one another? Two ways. One, with the old way, when you comment on a PR (or
line), the comment is made immediately. It's saved instantly to the GitHub
database, and a notification email is sent to everyone subscribed to the PR.
With the new way, the comment is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; made immediately.  Instead, you start
a "review", which postpones all comments from being published until you scroll
to the top and press a button ("Review changes"). &lt;strong&gt;Did you forget to scroll
to the top and press that button? Oh well, your comments never got sent to
anyone.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I've been told by some people that delayed commenting is a feature that
they like. I can see how fewer total emails could be nice. &lt;strong&gt;But if you just
want a way to delay comments, why do you need distinct commenting UIs?&lt;/strong&gt;
Couldn't the same thing be achieved via a user setting (I highly suspect that
any given person will either like or dislike delayed commenting universally)?
Or with a checkbox next to the comment button, like "delay notifications for
this comment"? You can probably guess by now which of the two commenting
systems I prefer. But guess what happens when I press the "Cmd-Enter" keyboard
shortcut that's been hard-wired into my brain to submit a comment? I'll give
you a hint: the
result
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/781949163562999808"&gt;does not make me happy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second distinction between normal, old-fashioned commenting and the
new-fangled reviews system is that when you finalize a review, you can elect
to "approve" or "reject" the pull request. This approval or rejection gets set
as a special status on the pull request. This status, for me personally, is
the only feature here that I've been wanting. It turns out, however, that it's
completely broken, and useless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's my problem. We have, at the time of
writing, &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pulls"&gt;382 open pull requests&lt;/a&gt; in
SymPy. A lot of these are old, and need to be triaged. But the problem from my
point of view is the new ones. When I look through the list of pull requests,
I want to be able to know, at a glance, which ones are "reviewable". For me,
this means two things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tests pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No other reviewer (myself included) has already requested changes, which
still need to be made by the PR author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Point 1 is really easy to see. In the pull request list, there is a nice green
checkmark if Travis passed and a red X if it failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/prlist.png" width="608"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second point is a disaster. Unfortunately, there's no simple way to do
this. You might suggest adding a special label, like "Needs changes", to pull
requests that have been reviewed. The problem with this is that the label
won't go away when the changes have been made. And to worsen things, people
who don't have push access (in the list above, only two PR authors have push
access, and one of them is me), cannot add or remove labels on pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another thing
that
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/771393023389339649"&gt;has been suggested to me&lt;/a&gt; is
an external "review" service that sets a status for a review. The problem with
this (aside from the fact that I couldn't find one that actually did the very
simple thing that I wanted), is that you now have to teach all your pull
request reviewers to use this service. You might as well forget about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having a first-class way in GitHub for reviewers to say "I approve these
changes" or "I don't approve these changes" would be a huge boon, because then
everyone would use it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So great right, this new Reviews feature is exactly what you want, you say.
You can now approve or reject pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well no, because GitHub managed to overengineer this feature to the point of
making it useless. This completely simple feature. All they had to do was
extend the status UI and add a simple "I approve/I reject" button. If they did
that, it would have worked perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the problems. First, the pull request list has no indication of
review status. Guess which pull requests in the above screenshot have reviews
(and which are positive and which are negative). You can't tell (for example,
the last one in the list has a negative review). If they were actually treated
like statuses, like the UI suggests that they would, you would at least see an
X on the ones that have negative reviews (positive reviews I'm much less
worried about; most people who review PRs have merge access, so if they like
the PR they can just merge it). I would suggest to GitHub to add, next to the
status checkbox, a picture of everyone who's made a review on the PR, with a
green checkmark or red X to indicate the type of review. Also, add buttons
(&lt;strong&gt;buttons&lt;/strong&gt;, not just buried advanced search options) to filter by reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OK, so that's a minor UI annoyance, but it gets worse. Next on the docket, &lt;strong&gt;you
can't review your own pull requests.&lt;/strong&gt; It's not allowed for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/reviews3.png" width="411"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now why would you want to review your own pull request, you might ask? Aren't
you always going to "approve" your own PR? Well, first off, no. There is such
a thing as
a &lt;a href="http://ben.balter.com/2015/12/08/types-of-pull-requests/"&gt;WIP PR&lt;/a&gt;. The
author setting a negative review on his own PR would be a great way to
indicate WIP status (especially given the way reviews work, see my next
gripe). Secondly, the "author" of a pull request is just the person who
clicked the "New pull request" button. That's not necessarily the only person
who has changes in the pull request. Thanks to the magic of how git works,
it's quite easy to have a pull request with commits from many people. Multiple
people pushing to a shared branch, with a matching pull request for discussion
(and easy viewing of new commits and diff) is a valid and useful workflow
(it's the only one I know of that works for writing collaborative prose). For
the &lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy-paper"&gt;SymPy paper&lt;/a&gt;, I wanted to use
GitHub Reviews to sign off on a common branch, but since I'm the one who
started the pull request, I couldn't do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next gripe, and this, I want to stress, makes the whole feature completely
useless for my needs: &lt;strong&gt;reviews do not reset when new commits are pushed&lt;/strong&gt;.
Now, I just outlined above two use-cases where you might want to do a review
that doesn't reset (marking WIP, and marking approval, although the second is
debatable), but both of those can easily be done by other means, like editing
the title of the PR, or old-fashioned commenting. The whole point of Reviews
(especially negative reviews), you'd think, would be to indicate to people
that the pull request, as it currently stands, needs new changes. A negative
review is like failing your "human" test suite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unlike your automated test suite, which reset and get a new go every time
you push a change (because hey, who knows, maybe the change ACTUALLY FIXED THE
ISSUE), reviews do not reset, unless the original reviewers explicitly change
them. So my dream of being able to glance at the pull request list and see
which PRs need changes has officially
been &lt;a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/pipe_dream"&gt;piped&lt;/a&gt;. Even if the list
actually showed what PRs have been reviewed, it would be a lie, because as
soon as the PR author pushes a change, the review status becomes potentially
outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, given the rocky start that this whole feature has had, I figured that
this was probably just a simple bug. But after I reported it to GitHub,
they've informed me that this is in fact &lt;em&gt;intended behavior&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make things worse, GitHub has another feature with Reviews,
called
&lt;a href="https://help.github.com/articles/approving-a-pull-request-with-required-reviews/"&gt;required reviews&lt;/a&gt;.
You can make it so that every pull request must receive at least one positive
review and zero negative reviews before it can be merged (go to the branch
settings for your repository). This works similar to required status checks,
which make it so that your tests must pass before a PR can be merged. In
practice, this means you need zero negative reviews, since anyone with push
access could just do a positive review before merging (although annoyingly,
you have to actually manually do it; IMHO, just requiring zero negative
reviews should be sufficient, since merging is implicitly a positive review).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can see that the above "feature" of reviews not resetting breaks the
whole thing. If someone negative reviews a PR, that one person has to go in
and change their review before it can be merged. And even if the author pushes
new changes to fix the issues outlined in the review, the PR cannot be merged
until the reviewer resets it. So this actually makes the reviewing situation
&lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt;, because now anyone who reviews a pull request at any point in time
has to go through with it all the way to the merge. I can't go to a PR that
someone requested changes for, which were later made by the author, and merge
it. I have to ping the reviewer and get them to change their review first.
Needless to say, we do not have this feature enabled for SymPy's repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I maybe see the intended use-case here. You want to make it so that
people's reviews are not forgotten or ignored. But that's completely foreign
to my own problems. I trust the SymPy community, and the people who have push
access to do due diligence before merging a pull request. And if a bad change
gets in, we can revert it. Maybe this feature matters more for projects that
continuously deploy. Likely most of the code internal at GitHub works like
that. But guess what GitHub, most of the code &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt; GitHub does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work like
that. You need to rethink this feature to support more than just your
use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think starting simple, say, just a simple "approve/reject" button on each
PR, which just adds an icon, and that's it, would have been a better approach.
Then they could have listened to the feedback on what sorts of things people
wanted it to be able to do (like setting a status, or showing up in the search
list, or "delayed commenting" if that's really what people want). This is how
GitHub used to do things. It's frustrating to see a feature implemented that
doesn't (yet) do quite what you want, but it's even more frustrating to see a
feature implemented that does all the things that you don't want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I'm a little mad here. I hope you enjoyed my rant. Here are what I see as
the problems with the "Reviews" feature. I don't know how to fix these
problems (I'm not a UI/UX guy. GitHub supposedly hires them, though).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now two distinct ways to comment on a PR (delayed and non-delayed).
There should be one (say, with a checkbox to delay commenting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you insist on keeping delayed commenting, let me turn it off by default
(default = the Cmd-Enter keyboard shortcut).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reviews button is buried on the diff page. I would put it under the
main PR comment box, and just reuse the same comment box.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reviews should show up in the pull request list. They should be filterable
with a nice UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me review my own pull requests. These can be excluded from required
reviews (that makes sense to me). Beyond that, there's no reason this
shouldn't be allowed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't require a positive review for required reviews, only zero negative
reviews. Merging a PR is implicitly positively reviewing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Allow reviews to reset when new commits are pushed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that the last point may not be what everyone wants. But GitHub needs to
think about UI, and defaults here. Right now, the UI looks like reviews are
like statuses, but they actually aren't because of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am dispirited to see GitHub release such a broken feature, but even the best
trip up sometimes. I'm not yet calling "doom" on GitHub. Everyone has
their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_USB_Mouse"&gt;hockey puck mice&lt;/a&gt;. I'm
actually hopeful that they can fix these issues, and implement a feature that
makes real headway into helping me solve one of my biggest problems on GitHub
right now, the reviewing of pull requests.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/github-reviews-gripes/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:12:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tuples</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, David Beazley made some tweets:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;At the bookstore. I'll admit I judge Python books by their tuple description. "Read only list?"  Back on the shelf.  Nope.&lt;/p&gt; David Beazley (@dabeaz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778634205395845120"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Usually there's a sentence nearby "sometimes you need a read only list." No. No, I haven't. Not in 20 years. Not even once. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt; David Beazley (@dabeaz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778635637457088512"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;My main objection is that "read only list" is a lazy description lacking thought. A red flag for every other topic that might be covered.&lt;/p&gt; David Beazley (@dabeaz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778639979052498944"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are quite a few good responses to these tweets, both from David and from
others (and from yours truly). I recommend reading the the thread (click on
the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778634205395845120"&gt;first tweet&lt;/a&gt; above).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to start off, I want to say that I respect the hell out of David Beazley.
The guy literally &lt;a href="http://www.dabeaz.com/cookbook.html"&gt;wrote the book&lt;/a&gt; on
Python, and he knows way more about Python than I ever will. He's also one of
the most entertaining Python people you can
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz"&gt;follow on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;. But hey, that doesn't mean I
can't disagree sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;List vs. Tuple. Fight!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you probably know, there are two "array" datatypes in Python, &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;sup id="fnref-list"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fn-list"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The primary difference between the two is that lists are &lt;em&gt;mutable&lt;/em&gt;,
that is you can change their entries and length after they are created, with
methods like &lt;code&gt;.append&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;+=&lt;/code&gt;. Tuples, on the other hand, are &lt;em&gt;immutable&lt;/em&gt;.
Once you create one, you cannot change it. This makes the implementation
simpler (and hence faster, although don't let anyone tell you you should use a
tuple just because it's faster). This, as
&lt;a href="http://nedbatchelder.com/blog/201608/lists_vs_tuples.html"&gt;Ned Batchelder&lt;/a&gt;
points out, is the only technical difference between the two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The the idea that particularly bugs me here is that tuples are primarily
useful as "record" datatypes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AllenDowney"&gt;@AllenDowney&lt;/a&gt; Better than "read-only-list." ;-).   Mainly looking for the tuple-as-record description. That's often what's missing.&lt;/p&gt; David Beazley (@dabeaz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778685294593716224"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuples are awesome for records. This is both by designsince they have a
fixed shape, the positions in a tuple can be "fixed" values, and by conventionif a
Python programmer sees parentheses instead of square brackets, he is more
likely to see the object as "record-like". The &lt;code&gt;namedtuple&lt;/code&gt; object in the standard library
takes the record idea further by letting you actually name the fields:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;collections&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;person&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;namedtuple&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'Person'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'name, age'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;person&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'Aaron'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;26&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Person&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'Aaron'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;age&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;26&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But is that really the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; place you'd want to use a tuple over a list?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider five other places you might encounter a tuple in Python, courtesy of
Allen Downey:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz"&gt;@dabeaz&lt;/a&gt; (1) tuple assignment (2) multiple return values (3) *args (4) output from zip, enumerate, etc (5) key in dictionary&lt;/p&gt; Allen Downey (@AllenDowney) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AllenDowney/status/778691102094176257"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In code these look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple assignments:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; (a, b) = 1, 2
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(yes, the parentheses are optional here, as they are in many places where a
tuple can be used, but this is still a tuple, or at least it looks like one ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple return values:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example,
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/os.html#os.walk"&gt;&lt;code&gt;os.walk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This is
for the most part a special case of using tuples as records.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;*args&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def f(*args):
...     print(type(args), args)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; f(1, 2, 3)
&amp;lt;class 'tuple'&amp;gt; (1, 2, 3)
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arbitrary positional function arguments are always stored as a &lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Return value from builtins &lt;code&gt;zip&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;enumerate&lt;/code&gt;, etc.:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; for i in zip(range(3), 'abc'):
...     print(i)
...
(0, 'a')
(1, 'b')
(2, 'c')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; for i in enumerate('abc'):
...     print(i)
...
(0, 'a')
(1, 'b')
(2, 'c')
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This also applies to the combinatoric generators in
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3.6/library/itertools.html"&gt;itertools&lt;/a&gt; (like
&lt;code&gt;product&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;combinations&lt;/code&gt;, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dictionary keys:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {
...     (0, 0): '.',
...     (0, 1): ' ',
...     (1, 0): '.',
...     (1, 1): ' ',
... }
{(0, 1): ' ', (1, 0): '.', (0, 0): '.', (1, 1): ' '}
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last one I find to be very important. You could arguably use a list for
the first four of Allen Downey's points&lt;sup id="fnref-assign"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fn-assign"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; (or Python could have, if it wanted to). But it
is
&lt;a href="https://asmeurer.github.io/blog/posts/what-happens-when-you-mess-with-hashing-in-python/"&gt;impossible&lt;/a&gt;
to meaningfully hash a mutable data structure in Python, and hashability is a
requirement for dictionary keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, be careful. Not all tuples are hashable. Tuples can contain
anything, but only tuples of immutable values are hashable. Consider&lt;sup id="fnref-TypeError"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fn-TypeError"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;])&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Such tuples are not hashable, and cannot be used as dictionary keys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"&amp;lt;ipython-input-39-36822ba665ca&amp;gt;"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="nb"&gt;hash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unhashable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;'list'&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Why is &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; the Default?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My second gripe here is this notion that your default ordered collection
object in Python should be &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;tuples&lt;/code&gt; are only to be used as "records",
or if you suspect &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; want to use it as a dictionary key. First off, you
never know when you'll want something to be hashable. Both dictionary keys and
&lt;code&gt;sets&lt;/code&gt; require hashability. Suppose you want to de-duplicate a collection of
sequences. If you represent the sequences with &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;, you'll either have to
write a custom loop that checks for duplicates, or manually convert them to
&lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt; and throw them in a &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;. If you start with &lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt;, you don't have
to worry about it (again, assuming the entries of the tuples are all hashable
as well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider another usage of tuples, which I consider to be
important, namely tree structures. Say you wanted a simple representation of a
Python syntax tree. You might represent &lt;code&gt;1 - 2*(-3 + 4)&lt;/code&gt; as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'-'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'*'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'+'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;'-'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This isn't really a record. The meaning of the entries in the tuples is
determined by the first value of the tuple, not position. In this example, the length
of the tuple also signifies meaning (binary vs. unary &lt;code&gt;-&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this looks familiar to you, it's because this is how the language Lisp
represents all programs. This is a common pattern.
&lt;a href="http://dask.pydata.org/en/latest/graphs.html"&gt;Dask graphs&lt;/a&gt; use tuples and
dictionaries to represent computations.
&lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/manipulation.html"&gt;SymPy expression trees&lt;/a&gt;
use tuples and Python classes to represent symbolic mathematical expressions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why use tuples over lists here? Suppose you had an object like the one
above, but using lists: &lt;code&gt;['-', 1, ['*', 2, ['+', ['-', 3], 4]]]&lt;/code&gt;. If you
discover you need to use this as a dictionary key, or want to put it in a
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;, you would need to convert this to a hashable object. To do this you
need to write a function that recursively converts each &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; to a &lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt;.
See how long it takes you to write that function correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mutability is Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More to the point, however, mutability is bad. I counted 12 distinct methods
on &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; that mutate it (how many can you remember off the top of your
head?&lt;sup id="fnref-mutate"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fn-mutate"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;). &lt;em&gt;Any&lt;/em&gt; function that gets access to a list can mutate it,
using any one of these methods. All it takes is for someone to forget that
&lt;code&gt;+=&lt;/code&gt; mutates a list (and that they should copy it first) for code completely
distant from the origin definition to cause issues. The hardest bug I ever
debugged had a three character
&lt;a href="https://github.com/inducer/pudb/commit/b979fc5909c8d731eb907fc25f4e97904fb7cbbd"&gt;fix&lt;/a&gt;,
adding &lt;code&gt;[:]&lt;/code&gt; to copy a global list that I was (accidentally) mutating. It took
me a several hour airplane ride and some deep dark magic that I'll leave for
another blog post to discover the source of my problems (the problems I was
having appeared to be quite distant from the actual source).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A Better "Default"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose that Python code in general would be vastly improved if people used
&lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt; as the default ordered collection, and only switched to &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; if
mutation was necessary (it's less necessary than you think; you can always
copy a tuple instead of mutating it). I agree with David Beazley that you
don't "sometimes need a read only list". Rather, you "sometimes need a
writable tuple".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes more sense than defaulting to &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;, and only switching to &lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt;
when hashability is needed, or when some weird "rule of thumb" applies that
says that you should use &lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt; if you have a "record". Maybe there's a good
reason that &lt;code&gt;*args&lt;/code&gt; and almost all builtin and standard library functions
return tuples instead of lists. It's harder to accidentally break someone
else's code, or have someone else accidentally break your code, when your data
structures are immutable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-list"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to avoid saying "a tuple is an immutable list", since "list"
can be interpreted in two ways, as an English word meaning "ordered
collection" (in
which case, the statement is true), or as the Python type &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; (in which
case, the statement is false&lt;code&gt;tuple&lt;/code&gt; is not a subclass of &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fnref-list" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-assign"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; [a, b] = 1, 2
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;works.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fnref-assign" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-mutate"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div id="spoiler" style="display:none"&gt;
&lt;code&gt;__delitem__&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;__iadd__&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;__imul__&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;__setitem__&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;append&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;clear&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;extend&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;insert&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;pop&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;remove&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;reverse&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;sort&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;button title="Click to show/hide content" type="button" onclick="if(document.getElementById('spoiler') .style.display=='none')
{document.getElementById('spoiler')
.style.display=''}else{document.getElementById('spoiler')
.style.display='none'}"&gt;Show/hide answer&lt;/button&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fnref-mutate" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-TypeError"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the tweets from the conversation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-conversation="none" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer"&gt;@asmeurer&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AllenDowney"&gt;@AllenDowney&lt;/a&gt; As yes:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;t = (1,2, [3, 4])&lt;br&gt;t[2] += [5,6]&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;;-)&lt;/p&gt; David Beazley (@dabeaz) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dabeaz/status/778697399975813120"&gt;September 21, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is similar to this example. But
it turns out this one doesn't work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code literal-block"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; t = (1,2, [3, 4])
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; t[2] += [5,6]
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
TypeError: 'tuple' object does not support item assignment
&lt;/pre&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have no idea why. It seems to me that it should work. &lt;code&gt;t[2]&lt;/code&gt; is a list
and &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; has &lt;code&gt;__iadd__&lt;/code&gt; defined. It seems that Python gets kind of weird
about things on the left-hand side of an assignment. &lt;strong&gt;EDIT:
&lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/29747466/161801"&gt;Here's&lt;/a&gt; why.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/#fnref-TypeError" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/tuples/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 02:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moving Away from Python 2</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;About a month ago I tweeted this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Thought: get the maintainers of a bunch of big Python libraries to sign something saying that they WILL drop Python 2.7 support in 2020.&lt;/p&gt; Aaron Meurer (@asmeurer) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/712304912428875776"&gt;March 22, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT: Some people have started working on making this happen. See
&lt;a href="https://python3statement.github.io/"&gt;https://python3statement.github.io/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those of you who don't know, Python 2.7 is
&lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/devguide/#status-of-python-branches"&gt;slated&lt;/a&gt; to reach
end-of-life in 2020 (originally, it was slated to end in 2015, but it was
extended in 2014, due to the extraordinary difficulty of moving to a newer
version). "End-of-life" means absolutely no more support from the core Python
team, even for security updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this post because I want to clarify why I think this should be
done, and to clear up some misconceptions, the primary one being that this
represents library developers being antagonistic against those who want or
have to use Python 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm writing this from my perspective as a library developer. I'm the lead
developer of &lt;a href="http://www.sympy.org/"&gt;SymPy&lt;/a&gt;, and I have sympathies for
developers of other libraries.&lt;sup id="fnref-sympy"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fn-sympy"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I say this because my idea may seem a bit
in tension with "users" (even though I hate the "developer/user" distinction).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Python 2&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons why I think libraries should drop (and announce that
they will drop) Python 2 support by 2020 (actually earlier, say 2018 or 2019,
depending on how core the library is).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, library developers have to be the leaders here. This is apparent from
the historical move to Python 3 up to this point. Consider the three (not
necessarily disjoint) classes of people: CPython core developers, library
developers, and users. The core developers were the first to move to Python 3,
since they were the ones who wrote it. They were also the ones who provided
the messaging around Python 3, which has varied over time. In my opinion, it
should have been and should be more forceful.&lt;sup id="fnref-core"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fn-core"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Then you have the library
developers and the users. A chief difference here is that users are probably
going to be using only one version of Python. In order for them to switch that
version to Python 3, all the libraries that they use need to support it. This
took some time, since library developers saw little impetus to support Python
3 when no one was using it (Catch 22), and to worsen the situation, versions
of Python older than 2.6 made
&lt;a href="https://asmeurersympy.wordpress.com/2013/08/22/python-3-single-codebase-vs-2to3/"&gt;single codebase compatibility&lt;/a&gt;
almost impossible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, though, &lt;a href="http://py3readiness.org/"&gt;almost all libraries&lt;/a&gt; support Python
3, and we're reaching a point where those that don't have
forks that do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it only happened &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the library developers transitioned. I believe
libraries need to be the leaders in moving away from Python 2 as well. It's
important to do this for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python 2.7 support ends in 2020. That means all updates, including security
  updates. For all intents and purposes, Python 2.7 becomes an insecure
  language to use at that point in time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supporting two major versions of Python is technical debt for every project
  that does it. While writing cross compatible code is
  &lt;a href="http://python-future.org/"&gt;easier than ever&lt;/a&gt;, it still remains true that
  you have to remember to add &lt;code&gt;__future__&lt;/code&gt; imports to the top of every file,
  to import all relevant builtins from your compatibility file or library, and
  to run all your tests in both Python 2 and 3. Supporting both versions is a
  major cognitive burden to library developers, as they always have to be
  aware of important differences in the two languages. Developers on any
  library that does anything with strings will need to understand how things
  work in both Python 2 and 3, and the often obscure workarounds required for
  things to work in both (pop quiz: how do you write Unicode characters to a
  file in a Python 2/3 compatible way?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of Python 3's
  &lt;a href="https://asmeurer.github.io/python3-presentation/slides.html"&gt;new syntax features&lt;/a&gt;
  (i.e., features that are impossible to use in Python 2) only matter for
  library developers. A great example of this is
  &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-3102/"&gt;keyword-only arguments&lt;/a&gt;. From an
  API standpoint, almost every instance of keyword arguments should be
  implemented as keyword-only arguments. This avoids mistakes that come from
  the antipattern of passing keyword arguments without naming the keyword, and
  allows the argspec of the function to be expanded in the future without
  breaking API.&lt;sup id="fnref-swift"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fn-swift"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason I think library developers should agree to drop Python 2
support by 2020 is completely selfish. A response that I heard on that tweet
(as well as elsewhere), was that libraries should provide carrots, not sticks.
In other words, instead of forcing people off of Python 2, we should make them
want to come to Python 3. There are some issues with this argument. First,
Python 3 already has
&lt;a href="https://asmeurer.github.io/python3-presentation/slides.html"&gt;tons of carrots&lt;/a&gt;.
Honestly, not being terrible at Unicode ought to be a carrot in its own right.&lt;sup id="fnref-unicode"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fn-unicode"&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't deal with strings, or do but don't care about those silly
foreigners with weird accents in their names, there are other major carrots as
well. For SymPy, the fact that 1/2 gives 0 in Python 2 has historically been a
major source of frustration for new users. Imagine writing out &lt;code&gt;1/2*x +
x**(1/2)*y*z - 3*z**2&lt;/code&gt; and wondering why half of what you wrote just
"disappeared" (granted, this was worse before we
&lt;a href="https://asmeurersympy.wordpress.com/2011/08/18/sqrtx-now-prints-as-sqrtx/"&gt;fixed the printers&lt;/a&gt;).
While &lt;code&gt;integer/integer&lt;/code&gt; not giving a rational number is a major
&lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/gotchas.html#two-final-notes-and"&gt;gotcha&lt;/a&gt;
for SymPy, giving a float is infinitely better than giving what is effectively
the wrong answer. Don't use strings or integers?
&lt;a href="https://asmeurer.github.io/python3-presentation/slides.html"&gt;I've got more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankly, if these "carrots" haven't convinced you yet, then I'll wager you're
not really the sort of person who is persuaded by carrots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, some "carrots" are impossible unless they are implemented in
libraries. While some features can be implemented in 2/3 compatible code and
only work in Python 3 (such as &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; matrix multiplication), others, such as
keyword-only arguments, can only be implemented in code that does not support
Python 2. Supporting them in Python 2 would be a net deficit of technical debt
(one can imagine, for instance, trying to support keyword-only arguments
manually using &lt;code&gt;**kwargs&lt;/code&gt;, or by using some monstrous meta-programming).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, as I said, I'm selfish. Python 3 &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; have carrots, and I want them.
As long as I have to support Python 2 in my code, I can't use keyword-only
arguments, or extended argument unpacking, or async/await, or any of the
dozens of features that can't be used in cross compatible code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A counterargument might be that instead of blocking users of existing
libraries, developers should create new libraries which are Python 3-only and
make use of new exciting features of Python 3 there. I agree we should do
that, but existing libraries are good too. I don't see why developers should
throw out all of a well-developed library just so they can use some Python
features that they are excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Legacy Python&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of people have taken to calling Python 2
"&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RipLegacyPython"&gt;legacy Python&lt;/a&gt;". This phrase is often
used condescendingly and
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/stephtdouglas/status/713433933040340993"&gt;angers a lot of people&lt;/a&gt;
(and indeed, this blog post is the first time I've used it myself). However, I
think Python 2 really should be seen this way, as a "legacy" system. If you
want to use it, for whatever your reasons, that's fine, but just as you
shouldn't expect to get any of the newest features of Python, you shouldn't
expect to be able to use the newest versions of your libraries. Those
libraries that have a lot of development resources may choose to support older
Python 2-compatible versions with bug and/or security fixes. Python 2 itself
will be supported for these until 2020. Those without resources probably won't
(keep in mind that you're using open source libraries without paying money for
them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get that some people have to use Python 2, for whatever reasons. But using
outdated software comes at a cost. Libraries have borne this technical debt
for the most part thus far, but they shouldn't be expected to bear it forever.
The debt will only increase, especially as the technical opportunity cost, if
you will, of not being able to use newer and shinier versions of Python 3
grows. The burden will have to shift at some point. Those with the financial
resources may choose to offload this debt to others,&lt;sup id="fnref-continuum"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fn-continuum"&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; say, by
backporting features or bugfixes to older library versions that support Python
2 (or by helping to move code to Python 3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to end by pointing out that if you are, for whatever reason, still
using Python 2, you may be worried that if libraries become Python 3-only and
start using Python 3 features, won't that break your code? The answer is no.
Assuming package maintainers mark the metadata on their packages correctly,
tools like pip and conda will not install non-Python 2 compatible versions
into Python 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't transitioned yet, and want to know more, a good place to start
is the &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/3/howto/pyporting.html"&gt;official docs&lt;/a&gt;. I also
highly recommend using &lt;a href="http://conda.pydata.org/docs/"&gt;conda&lt;/a&gt; environments, as
it will make it easy to separate your Python 2 code from your Python 3 code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-sympy"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that being said, the opinions here are entirely my own, and are
    don't necessarily represent those of other people, nor do they
    represent official SymPy policy (no decisions have been made by the
    community about this at this time).&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fnref-sympy" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-core"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It often feels like core Python itself doesn't really want people to
    use Python 3. It's little things, like
    &lt;a href="https://docs.python.org/library/"&gt;docs links&lt;/a&gt; that redirect to Python
    2, or &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0394/"&gt;PEP 394&lt;/a&gt;, which
    still says that the &lt;code&gt;python&lt;/code&gt; should always point to Python 2.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fnref-core" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-swift"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Swift, Apple's new language for iOS and OS X, function parameter
    names are effectively "keyword-only"
    &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/Swift_Programming_Language/Functions.html"&gt;by default&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fnref-swift" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-unicode"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of this, in conda, if you use Python 2 in the root
    environment, then installing into a path with non-ASCII characters is
    unsupported. This is common on Windows, because Windows by default
    uses the user's full name as the username, and the default conda
    install path is in the user directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unsupported except in Python 3, because to fix the issue,
every single place in conda where a string appears would have to be
changed to use a &lt;code&gt;unicode&lt;/code&gt; string in Python 2. The basic issue is that
things like &lt;code&gt;'' + u'i'&lt;/code&gt; raise &lt;code&gt;UnicodeDecodeError&lt;/code&gt; in Python 2 (even
though &lt;code&gt;'' + 'i'&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;u'' + 'i'&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;u'' + u'i'&lt;/code&gt; all work fine).
You can read a more in-depth description of the problem
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/9692#issuecomment-126162173"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Incidentally, this is also why you should never use &lt;code&gt;from __future__
import unicode_literals&lt;/code&gt; in Python 2, in my opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I no longer work on conda, but as far as I know, the
&lt;a href="https://github.com/conda/conda/issues/1180"&gt;issue&lt;/a&gt; remains unfixed.
Of course, this whole thing works just fine if conda is run in Python
3.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fnref-unicode" title="Jump back to footnote 4 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-continuum"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that legitimately interests you, I
    &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/pwang/status/712780279211884546"&gt;hear Continuum&lt;/a&gt;
    may be able to help you.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/#fnref-continuum" title="Jump back to footnote 5 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/moving-away-from-python-2/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2016 18:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What happens when you mess with hashing in Python</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/what-happens-when-you-mess-with-hashing-in-python/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is based off a Jupyter notebook I made in 2013. You can download
the original &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/asmeurer/6046766"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. That notebook
was based off a
&lt;a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/What-happens-when-you-mess-with-hashing"&gt;wiki page&lt;/a&gt;
on the SymPy wiki, which in turn was based on
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#%21msg/sympy/pJ2jg2csKgU/0nn21xqZEmwJ"&gt;a message&lt;/a&gt;
to the SymPy mailing list.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is hashing?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we start, let's have a brief introduction to hashing. A
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hash_function"&gt;&lt;em&gt;hash function&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is a function
that maps a set of objects to a set of integers. There are many kinds of hash
functions, which satisfy many different properties, but the most important
property that must be satisfied by any hash function is that it be a function
(in the mathematical sense), that is, if two objects are equal, then their
hash should also be equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, the set of integers that the hash function maps to is much smaller
than the set of objects, so that there will be multiple objects that hash to
the same value. However, generally for a hash function to be useful, the set
of integers should be large enough, and the hash function well distributed
enough that if two objects hash to the same value, then they are very likely
to be equal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, a hash function &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; satisfy the property:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If two objects are equal, then their hashes should be equal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; hash function should satisfy the property:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If two objects have the same hash, then they are likely to be the same
object.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there are generally more possible objects than hash values, two objects
may hash to the same value. This is called a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hash_collision"&gt;hash collision&lt;/a&gt;, and anything
that deals with hashes should be able to deal with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This won't be discussed here, but an additional property that a good hash
function should satisfy to be useful is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The hash of an object should be cheap to compute.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is it used for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we have a hash function that satisfies the above properties, then we can
use it to create from a collection of objects something called a &lt;em&gt;hash table&lt;/em&gt;.
Suppose we have a collection of objects, and given any object, we want to be
able to compute very quickly if that object belongs to our collection. We
could store these objects in an ordered array, but then to determine if it is
in the array, we would have to search potentially through every element of the
array (in other words, an \(O(n)\)) algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With hashing, we can do better. We create what is known as a
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hash_table"&gt;&lt;em&gt;hash table&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Instead of storing
the objects in an ordered array, we create an array of buckets, each
corresponding to some hash values. We then hash each object, and store it into
the array corresponding to its hash value (if there are more hash values than
buckets, we distribute them using a second hash function, which can be as
simple as taking the modulus with respect to the number of buckets, &lt;code&gt;% n&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This image from
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Hash_table_3_1_1_0_1_0_0_SP.svg"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
shows an example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/7/7d/Hash_table_3_1_1_0_1_0_0_SP.svg" alt="img"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To determine if an object is in a hash table, we only have to hash the object,
and look in the bucket corresponding to that hash. This is an \(O(1)\)
algorithm, assuming we have a good hash function, because each bucket will
generally hold very few objects, possibly even none.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: there are some additional things that need to be done to handle hash
collisions, but the basic idea is the same, and as long as there aren't too
many hash collisions, which should happen if hash values are evenly
distributed and the size of the hash table is large compared to the number of
objects stored in it, the average time to determine if an object is in the
hash table is still \(O(1)\).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hashing in Python&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Python has a built in function that performs a hash called &lt;code&gt;hash()&lt;/code&gt;.  For many
objects, the hash is not very surprising.  Note, the hashes you see below may
not be the same ones you see if you run the examples, because Python hashing
depends on the architecture of the machine you are running on, and, in newer
versions of Python, hashes are randomized for security purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(10)
10
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(()) # An empty tuple
3527539
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash('a')
12416037344
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, not all objects are hashable. For example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash([]) # An empty list
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
TypeError: unhashable type: 'list'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is because Python has an additional restriction on hashing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In order for an object to be hashable, it must be immutable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is important basically because we want the hash of an object to remain
the same across the object's lifetime. But if we have a mutable object, then
that object itself can change over its lifetime. But then according to our
first bullet point above, that object's hash has to change too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This restriction simplifies hash tables. If we allowed an object's hash to
change while it is in a hash table, we would have to move it to a different
bucket. Not only is this costly, but the hash table would have to &lt;em&gt;notice&lt;/em&gt;
that this happened; the object itself doesn't know that it is sitting in a
hash table, at least not in the Python implementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python, there are two objects that correspond to hash tables, &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;. A &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; is a special kind of hash table called an
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associative_array"&gt;&lt;em&gt;associative array&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. An
associative array is a hash table where each element of the hash table points
to another object. The other object itself is not hashed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think of an associative array as a generalization of a regular array (like a
&lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;). In a &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt;, objects are associated to nonnegative integer indices,
like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l = ['a', 'b', 7]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l[0]
'a'
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l[2]
7
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an associative array (i.e., a &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt;) we can index objects by anything, so
long as the key is hashable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d = {0: 'a', 'hello': ['world']}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d[0]
'a'
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d['hello']
['world']
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that only the keys need to be hashable. The values can be anything, even
unhashable objects like lists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The uses for associative arrays are boundless. &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; is one of the most
useful data types in the Python language. Some example uses are&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extension of &lt;code&gt;list&lt;/code&gt; with "missing values". For example, &lt;code&gt;{0: 'a', 2: 7}&lt;/code&gt;
would correspond to the above list &lt;code&gt;l&lt;/code&gt; with the value &lt;code&gt;'b'&lt;/code&gt; corresponding to
the key &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; removed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Representation of a mathematical function with a finite domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A poor-man's database (the Wikipedia image above is an associative array
mapping names to telephone numbers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementing a &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/q/60208/161801"&gt;Pythonic version&lt;/a&gt;
of the switch-case statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other type of hash table, &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;, more closely matches the definition I
gave above for a hash table. A &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; is just a container of hashable
objects. &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;s are unordered, and can only contain one of each object (this
is why they are called "sets," because this matches the mathematical
definition of a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Set_(mathematics)"&gt;set&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Python 2.7 or later, you can create a set with &lt;code&gt;{&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;}&lt;/code&gt;, like &lt;code&gt;{a, b, c}&lt;/code&gt;. Otherwise, use &lt;code&gt;set([a, b, c])&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s = {0, (), '2'}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s
{0, '2', ()}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s.add(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s
{0, 1, '2', ()}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s.add(0)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; s
{0, 1, '2', ()}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A final note: &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; are themselves mutable, and hence not hashable!
There is an immutable version of &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; called &lt;code&gt;frozenset&lt;/code&gt;. There are no
immutable dictionaries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; f = frozenset([0, (), '2'])
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; f
frozenset({0, '2', ()})
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(f)
-7776452922777075760
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; # A frozenset, unlike a set, can be used as a dictionary key
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d[f] = 'a set'
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d
{0: 'a', frozenset({0, '2', ()}): 'a set', 'hello': ['world']}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating your own hashable objects&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we move on, there is one final thing we need to know about hashing in
Python, which is how to create hashes for custom objects. By default, if we
create an object, it will be hashable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class Nothing(object):
...     pass
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; N = Nothing()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(N)
270498113
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementation-wise, the hash is &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/a/33572401/161801"&gt;based
on&lt;/a&gt; object's &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;, which
corresponds to its position in memory. This satisfies the above conditions: it
is (extremely) cheap to compute, and since by default objects in Python
compare unequal to one another, objects with different hashes will be unequal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; M = Nothing()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; M == N
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(M)
270498117
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(M) == hash(N)
False
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To define a hash function for an object, define the &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class HashToOne(object):
...     def __hash__(self):
...         return 1
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; HTO = HashToOne()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(HTO)
1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To set an object as not hashable, set &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class NotHashable(object):
...     __hash__ = None
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; NH = NotHashable()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(NH)
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
TypeError: unhashable type: 'NotHashable'
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to override the equality operator &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;, define &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class AlwaysEqual(object):
...     def __eq__(self, other):
...         if isinstance(other, AlwaysEqual):
...             return True
...         return False
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 = AlwaysEqual()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE2 = AlwaysEqual()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 == AE2
True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the key points that I hope you will take away from this post is that if
you override &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt; and you want a hashable object, you &lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; also
override &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; to agree. Note that Python 3 will actually require this:
in Python 3, if you override &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;, it automatically sets &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; to
&lt;code&gt;None&lt;/code&gt;, making the object unhashable. You need to manually override &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt;
to make it hashable again. But that's as far as Python goes in enforcing these
rules, as we will see below. In particular, Python will never actually check
that your &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; actually agrees with your &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Messing with hashing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now to the fun stuff. What happens if we break some of the invariants that
Python expects of hashing. Python expects two key invariants to hold&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The hash of an object does not change across the object's lifetime (in
other words, a hashable object should be immutable).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;a == b&lt;/code&gt; implies &lt;code&gt;hash(a) == hash(b)&lt;/code&gt; (note that the reverse might not
hold in the case of a hash collision).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we shall see, Python expects, but does not enforce either of these.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example 1: Mutating a hash&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's break rule 1 first. Let's create an object with a hash, and then change
that object's hash over its lifetime, and see what sorts of things can happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class Bad(object):
...     def __init__(self, hash): # The object's hash will be hash
...         self.hash = hash
...     def __hash__(self):
...         return self.hash
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = Bad(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(b)
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d = {b:42}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d[b]
42
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.hash = 2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(b)
2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d[b]
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
KeyError: &amp;lt;__main__.Bad object at 0x1047e7438&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, we implicitly changed the hash of &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; by mutating the attribute of &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;
that is used to compute the hash. As a result, the object is no longer found
in a dictionary, which uses the hash to find the object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The object is still there, we just can't access it any more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d
{&amp;lt;__main__.Bad object at 0x1047e7438&amp;gt;: 42}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Python doesn't prevent me from doing this. We could make it if we
want (e.g., by making &lt;code&gt;__setattr__&lt;/code&gt; raise &lt;code&gt;AttributeError&lt;/code&gt;), but even then we
could forcibly change it by modifying the object's &lt;code&gt;__dict__&lt;/code&gt;. We could try
some more fancy things using descriptors, metaclasses, and/or
&lt;code&gt;__getattribute__&lt;/code&gt;, but even then, if we knew what was happening, we could
probably find a way to change it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what is meant when people say that Python is a "consenting adults"
language. You are expected to not try to break things, but generally aren't
prevented from doing so if you try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example 2: More mutation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's try something even more crazy. Let's make an object that hashes to a
different value each time we look at the hash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class DifferentHash(object):
...     def __init__(self):
...         self.hashcounter = 0
...     def __hash__(self):
...         self.hashcounter += 1
...         return self.hashcounter
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DH = DifferentHash()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(DH)
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(DH)
2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(DH)
3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, if we use &lt;code&gt;DH&lt;/code&gt; as a key to a dictionary, then it will not work,
because we will run into the same issue we had with &lt;code&gt;Bad&lt;/code&gt;. But what about
putting &lt;code&gt;DH&lt;/code&gt; in a &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset = {DH, DH, DH}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset
{&amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woah! We put the exact same object in a &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; three times, and it appeared all
three times. This is not what is supposed to happen with a set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {1, 1, 1}
{1}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happens when we do stuff with &lt;code&gt;DHset&lt;/code&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset.remove(DH)
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;", line 1, in &amp;lt;module&amp;gt;
KeyError: &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash object at 0x1047e75f8&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That didn't work, because &lt;code&gt;set.remove&lt;/code&gt; searches for an object by its hash,
which is different by this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's make a copy of &lt;code&gt;DHset&lt;/code&gt;. The &lt;code&gt;set.copy&lt;/code&gt; method will create a shallow
copy (meaning that the set container itself will be different, according to
&lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt; comparison, but the objects themselves will the same, according to &lt;code&gt;is&lt;/code&gt;
comparison).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset2 = DHset.copy()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset2 == DHset
True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything is fine so far. This object is only going to cause trouble if
something recomputes its hash. But remember that the whole reason that we had
trouble with something like &lt;code&gt;Bad&lt;/code&gt; above is that Python &lt;em&gt;doesn't&lt;/em&gt; recompute
that hash of an object, unless it has to. So let's do something that will
force it to do so: let's pop an object from one of the sets and add it back
in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; D = DHset.pop()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset.add(D)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset
{&amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset2
{&amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.DifferentHash at 0x101f79f50&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; DHset == DHset2
False
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There we go. By removing it from the set, we made the set forget about its
hash, so it had to be recomputed when we added it again. This version of
&lt;code&gt;DHset&lt;/code&gt; now has a &lt;code&gt;DH&lt;/code&gt; with a different hash than it had before. Thinking back
to &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt; being a hash table, in this &lt;code&gt;DHset&lt;/code&gt;, the three &lt;code&gt;DH&lt;/code&gt; objects are in
different "buckets" than they were in before. &lt;code&gt;DHset.__eq__(DHset2)&lt;/code&gt; notices
that the bucket structure is different right away and returns &lt;code&gt;False&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, what hash value are we up to these days?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(DH)
9
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example 3: When &lt;code&gt;a == b&lt;/code&gt; does not imply &lt;code&gt;hash(a) == hash(b)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let's look at point 2. What happens if we create an object with &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;
that disagrees with &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt;. For Python 2, we already have made a class like
this, the &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; object above. Instances of &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; will always
compare equal to one another, but they will not have the same hash, because
they will use &lt;code&gt;object&lt;/code&gt;'s default &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; of &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;. For Python 3, however,
&lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; is automatically set as unhashable because we overrode &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;
without also overriding &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post originally used the &lt;code&gt;AE1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;AE2&lt;/code&gt; objects we created above
for the next example, but to make it work in both Python 2 and 3, let's create
a custom &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; subclass that is hashable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-python"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class AlwaysEqualHashable(AlwaysEqual):
...     def __hash__(self):
...         return id(self)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 = AlwaysEqualHashable()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE2 = AlwaysEqualHashable()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(AE1)
270498221
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(AE2)
270498197
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(AE1) == hash(AE2)
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 == AE2
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {AE1, AE2}
{&amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79950&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79ad0&amp;gt;}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can already see that we have broken one of the key properties of a &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;,
which is that it does not contain the same object twice (remember that &lt;code&gt;AE1&lt;/code&gt;
and &lt;code&gt;AE2&lt;/code&gt; should be considered the "same object" because &lt;code&gt;AE1 == AE2&lt;/code&gt; is
&lt;code&gt;True&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can lead to subtle issues. For example, suppose we had a list and we
wanted to remove all the duplicate items from it. An easy way to do this is to
convert the list to a set and then convert it back to a list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l = ['a', 'a', 'c', 'a', 'c', 'b']
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; list(set(l))
['a', 'b', 'c']
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this method is obviously not going to work for a list of &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqualHashable&lt;/code&gt; objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE3 = AlwaysEqualHashable()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; l = [AE1, AE1, AE3, AE2, AE3]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; list(set(l))
[&amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x102c1d590&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79ad0&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79950&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, what happened here is that the equality that we defined on
&lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; was essentially ignored. We got a list of unique items by &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;,
instead of by &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt;. You can imagine that if &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt; were something a
little less trivial, where some, but not all, objects are considered equal,
that this could lead to very subtle issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is an issue with the above algorithm. It isn't stable, that is, it
removes the ordering that we had on the list. We could do this better by
making a new list, and looping through the old one, adding elements to the new
list if they aren't already there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def uniq(l):
...     newl = []
...     for i in l:
...         if i not in newl:
...             newl.append(i)
...     return newl
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq(['a', 'a', 'c', 'a', 'c', 'b'])
['a', 'c', 'b']
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq([AE1, AE1, AE3, AE2, AE3])
[&amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79ad0&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, we used &lt;code&gt;in&lt;/code&gt;, which uses &lt;code&gt;==&lt;/code&gt;, so we got only one unique element of
the list of &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqual&lt;/code&gt; objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is an issue with this algorithm as well. Checking if something is in
a list is \(O(n)\), but we have an object that allows checking in \(O(1)\)
time, namely, a &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;. So a more efficient version might be to create a set
alongside the new list for containment checking purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; def uniq2(l):
...     newl = []
...     newlset = set()
...     for i in l:
...         if i not in newlset:
...             newl.append(i)
...             newlset.add(i)
...     return newl
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq2(['a', 'a', 'c', 'a', 'c', 'b'])
['a', 'c', 'b']
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq2([AE1, AE1, AE3, AE2, AE3])
[&amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79ad0&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x102c1d590&amp;gt;,
 &amp;lt;__main__.AlwaysEqualHashable at 0x101f79950&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bah! Since we used a set, we compared by hashing, not equality, so we are left
with three objects again. Notice the extremely subtle difference
here. Basically, it is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 in {AE2}
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 in [AE2]
True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set containment uses hashing; list containment uses equality. If the two don't
agree, then the result of your algorithm will depend on which one you use!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, as you might expect, dictionary containment also uses hashing, and
tuple containment uses equality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 in {AE2: 42}
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; AE1 in (AE2,)
True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Example 4: Caching hashing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever want to add subtle bizarreness to a system, add some sort of
caching, and then do it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we noted in the beginning, one important property of a hash function is
that it is quick to compute. A nice way to achieve this for heavily cached
objects is to cache the value of the cache on the object, so that it only
needs to be computed once. The pattern (which is modeled after SymPy's
&lt;code&gt;Basic&lt;/code&gt;) is something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; class HashCache(object):
...     def __init__(self, arg):
...         self.arg = arg
...         self.hash_cache = None
...     def __hash__(self):
...         if self.hash_cache is None:
...             self.hash_cache = hash(self.arg)
...         return self.hash_cache
...     def __eq__(self, other):
...         if not isinstance(other, HashCache):
...             return False
...         return self.arg == other.arg
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;HashCache&lt;/code&gt; is nothing more than a small wrapper around a hashable argument,
which caches its hash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash('a')
12416037344
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache('a')
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(a)
12416037344
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For ordinary Python builtins, simply recomputing the hash will be faster than
the attribute lookup used by &lt;code&gt;HashCache&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Note: This uses the &lt;code&gt;%timeit&lt;/code&gt; magic
from IPython. &lt;code&gt;%timeit&lt;/code&gt; only works when run in IPython or Jupyter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; %timeit hash('a')
10000000 loops, best of 3: 69.9 ns per loop
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; %timeit hash(a)
1000000 loops, best of 3: 328 ns per loop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for a custom object, computing the hash may be more computationally
expensive. As hashing is supposed to agree with equality (as I hope you've
realized by now!), if computing equality is expensive, computing a hash
function that agrees with it might be expensive as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple example of where this might be useful, consider a highly nested
tuple, an object whose hash that is relatively expensive to compute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = ()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; for i in range(1000):
...     a = (a,)
...
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; A = HashCache(a)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; %timeit hash(a)
100000 loops, best of 3: 9.61 s per loop
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; %timeit hash(A)
1000000 loops, best of 3: 325 ns per loop
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, we haven't done anything wrong. &lt;code&gt;HashCache&lt;/code&gt;, as you may have noticed,
has &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt; defined correctly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; HashCache(1) == HashCache(2)
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; HashCache(1) == HashCache(1)
True
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what happens if we mutate a &lt;code&gt;HashCache&lt;/code&gt;. This is different from examples 1
and 2 above, because we will be mutating what happens with equality testing,
but not the hash (because of the cache).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the below example, recall that small integers hash to themselves, so
&lt;code&gt;hash(1) == 1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;hash(2) == 2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d = {a: 42}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a.arg = 2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(a)
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; d[a]
42
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we cached the hash of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;, which was computed as soon as we created
the dictionary &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;, it remained unchanged when modified the arg to be
&lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;. Thus, we can still find the key of the dictionary. But since we have
mutated &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;, the equality testing on it has changed. This means that, as with
the previous example, we are going to have issues with dicts and sets keeping
unique keys and entries (respectively).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = HashCache(2)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(a)
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(b)
2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.arg = 1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a == b
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(a) == hash(b)
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {a, b}
{&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache at 0x102c32050&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashCache at 0x102c32450&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq([a, b])
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache at 0x102c32050&amp;gt;]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq2([a, b])
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache at 0x102c32050&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashCache at 0x102c32450&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we mutate &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; so that it compares equal to &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;, we start to have the same sort of issues that we had in example 3 with &lt;code&gt;AlwaysEqualHashable&lt;/code&gt;. Let's look at an instant replay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = HashCache(2)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.arg = 1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(a == b)
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(hash(a) == hash(b))
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print({a, b})
{&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32a10&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32a50&amp;gt;]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq2([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32a50&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wait a minute, this time it's different! Comparing it to above, it's pretty
easy to see what was different this time. We left out the part where we showed
the hash of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;. When we did that the first time, it cached the hash
of &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, making it forever be &lt;code&gt;2&lt;/code&gt;, but when we didn't do it the second time,
the hash had not been cached yet, so the first time it is computed (in the
&lt;code&gt;print(hash(a) == hash(b))&lt;/code&gt; line), &lt;code&gt;b.arg&lt;/code&gt; has already been changed to &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And herein lies the extreme subtlety: if you mutate an object with that hashes
its cache like this, you will run into issues &lt;strong&gt;only if&lt;/strong&gt; you had already
called some function that hashed the object somewhere. Now just about anything
might compute the hash of an object. Or it might not. For example, our &lt;code&gt;uniq2&lt;/code&gt;
function computes the hash of the objects in its input list, because it stores
them in a set, but &lt;code&gt;uniq&lt;/code&gt; does not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = HashCache(2)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq2([a, b])
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.arg = 1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(a == b)
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(hash(a) == hash(b))
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print({a, b})
{&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c50&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c10&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c50&amp;gt;]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq2([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c50&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c10&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashCache(1)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = HashCache(2)
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq([a, b])
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b.arg = 1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(a == b)
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(hash(a) == hash(b))
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print({a, b})
{&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32c90&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32bd0&amp;gt;]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(uniq2([a, b]))
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashCache object at 0x102c32bd0&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moral of this final example is that if you are going to cache something,
that something had better be immutable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is this: don't mess with hashing. The two invariants above are
important. Let's restate them here,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The hash of an object must not change across the object's lifetime (in
other words, a hashable object should be immutable).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;a == b&lt;/code&gt; implies &lt;code&gt;hash(a) == hash(b)&lt;/code&gt; (note that the reverse might not
hold in the case of a hash collision).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't follow these rules, you will run into very subtle issues, because
very basic Python operations expect these invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to be able to mutate an object's properties, you have two
options. First, make the object unhashable (set &lt;code&gt;__hash__ = None&lt;/code&gt;). You won't
be able to use it in sets or as keys to a dictionary, but you will be free to
change the object in-place however you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second option is to make all mutable properties non-dependent on hashing or
equality testing. This option works well if you just want to cache some
internal state that doesn't inherently change the object. Both &lt;code&gt;__eq__&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; should remain unchanged by changes to this state. You may also want
to make sure you use proper getters and setters to prevent modification of
internal state that equality testing and hashing does depend on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you choose this second option, however, be aware that Python considers it
fair game to swap out two identical immutable (i.e., hashable) objects at any
time. If &lt;code&gt;a == b&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; is hashable, Python (and Python libraries) are free
to replace &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; anywhere. For example, Python uses an optimization on
strings called &lt;em&gt;interning&lt;/em&gt;, where common strings are stored only once in
memory. A similar optimization is used in CPython for small integers. If store
something on &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; but not &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; and make &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt;'s hash ignore that data, you may
find that some function that should return &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; may actually return &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;. For
this reason, I generally don't recommend this second option unless you know
what you are doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, to keep invariant 2, here are some tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure that the parts of the object that you use to compare equality are
not themselves mutable. If they are, then your object cannot itself be
immutable. This means that if &lt;code&gt;a == b&lt;/code&gt; depends on &lt;code&gt;a.attr == b.attr&lt;/code&gt;, and
&lt;code&gt;a.attr&lt;/code&gt; is a list, then you will need to use a tuple instead (if you want
&lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; to be hashable).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't have to invent a hash function. If you find yourself doing
bitshifts and XORs, you're doing it wrong. Reuse Python's builtin hashable
objects. If the hash of your object should depend on the hash of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and
&lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;, define &lt;code&gt;__hash__&lt;/code&gt; to return &lt;code&gt;hash((a, b))&lt;/code&gt;. If the order of &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt;
does not matter, use &lt;code&gt;hash(frozenset([a, b]))&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't cache something unless you know that the entire cached state will not
be changed over the lifetime of the cache. Hashable objects are actually
great for caches. If they properly satisfy invariant 1, and all the state
that should be cached is part of the hash, then you will not need to
worry. And the best part is that you can just use &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; for your cache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you really need the performance or memory gains, don't make your
objects mutable. This makes programs much harder to reason about. Some
functional programming languages take this idea so far that they don't allow
any mutable objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't worry about the situation where &lt;code&gt;hash(a) == hash(b)&lt;/code&gt; but &lt;code&gt;a != b&lt;/code&gt;. This is a hash collision. Unlike the issues we looked at here, hash
collisions are expected and checked for in Python. For example, our
&lt;code&gt;HashToOne&lt;/code&gt; object from the beginning will always hash to 1, but different
instances will compare unequal. We can see that the right thing is done in
every case with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a = HashToOne()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; b = HashToOne()
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; a == b
False
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(a) == hash(b)
True
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; {a, b}
{&amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32a10&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32cd0&amp;gt;}
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq([a, b])
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32cd0&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32a10&amp;gt;]
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; uniq2([a, b])
[&amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32cd0&amp;gt;, &amp;lt;__main__.HashToOne at 0x102c32a10&amp;gt;]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only concern with hash collisions is that too many of them can remove
the performance gains of &lt;code&gt;dict&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;set&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, if you are writing something that uses an object's hash, remember
that hash collisions are possible and unavoidable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A classic example of a hash collision is &lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;-2&lt;/code&gt;. Remember I
mentioned above that small integers hash to themselves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(1)
1
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(-3)
-3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exception to this is &lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt;. The CPython interpreter uses &lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt; as an error
state, so -1 is not a valid hash value. Hence, &lt;code&gt;hash(-1)&lt;/code&gt; can't be &lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt;. So
the Python developers picked the next closest thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(-1)
-2
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; hash(-2)
-2
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to check if something handles hash collisions correctly, this is
a simple example.  I should also note that the fact that integers hash to
themselves is an implementation detail of CPython that may not be true in
alternate Python implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we didn't discuss this much here, but don't assume that the hash of
your object will be the same across Python sessions. In Python 3.3 and up,
hash values of strings are randomized from a value that is seeded when
Python starts up. This also affects any object whose hash is computed
from the hash of strings. In Python 2.7, you can enable hash randomization
with the &lt;code&gt;-R&lt;/code&gt; flag to the interpreter. The following are two different
Python sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(hash('a'))
-7750608935454338104
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt; print(hash('a'))
8897161376854729812
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/what-happens-when-you-mess-with-hashing-in-python/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2016 04:13:53 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"Doing Math with Python" by Amit Saha: Book Review</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/doing-math-with-python-by-amit-saha-book-review/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: No Starch Press has sent me a copy of this book for review purposes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SHORT VERSION: &lt;em&gt;Doing Math with Python&lt;/em&gt; is well written and introduces
topics in a nice, mathematical way. I would recommend it for new users of
SymPy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.nostarch.com/doingmathwithpython"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Doing Math with Python&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by
Amit Saha is a new book published by No Starch Press. The book shows how to
use Python to do high school-level mathematics. It makes heavy use of SymPy in
many chapters, and this review will focus mainly on those parts, as that is
the area I have expertise in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book assumes a basic understanding of programming in Python 3, as well as
the mathematics used (although advanced topics are explained). No prior
background in the libraries used, SymPy and matplotlib, is assumed. For this
reason, this book can serve as an introduction them. Each chapter ends with
some programming exercises, which range from easy exercises to more advanced
ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book has seven chapters. In the first chapter, "Working with numbers",
basic mathematics using pure Python is introduced (no SymPy yet). It should be
noted that Python 3 (not Python 2) is required for this book. One of the
earliest examples in the book (&lt;code&gt;3/2 == 1.5&lt;/code&gt;) will not work correctly without
it. I applaud this choice, although I might have added a more prominent
warning to wary users. (As a side note, in the appendix, it is recommended to
install Python via &lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/downloads"&gt;Anaconda&lt;/a&gt;, which I
also applaud). This chapter also introduces the &lt;code&gt;fractions&lt;/code&gt; module, which
seems odd since &lt;code&gt;sympy.Rational&lt;/code&gt; will be implicitly used for rational numbers
later in the text (to little harm, however, since SymPy automatically converts
&lt;code&gt;fractions.Fraction&lt;/code&gt; instances to &lt;code&gt;sympy.Rational&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In all, this chapter is a good introduction to the basics of the mathematics
of Python. There is also an introduction to variables and strings. However, as
I noted above, one should really have some background with basic Python before
reading this book, as concepts like flow control and function definition are
assumed (note: there is an appendix that goes over this).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapters 2 and 3 cover plotting with matplotlib and basic statistics,
respectively. I will not say much about the matplotlib chapter, since I know
only basic matplotlib myself. I will note that the chapter covers matplotlib
from a (high school) mathematics point of view, starting with a definition of
the Cartesian plane, which seems a fitting choice for the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3 shows how to do basic statistics (mean, median, standard deviation,
etc.) using pure Python. This chapter is clearly meant for pedagogical
purposes for basic statistics, since the basic functions &lt;code&gt;mean&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;median&lt;/code&gt;,
etc. are implemented from scratch (as opposed to using &lt;code&gt;numpy.mean&lt;/code&gt; or the
standard library &lt;code&gt;statistics.mean&lt;/code&gt;). This serves as a good introduction to
more Python concepts (like &lt;code&gt;collections.Counter&lt;/code&gt;) and statistics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the functions in this chapter assume that the data is the entire
population, not a sample. This is mentioned at the beginning of the chapter,
but not elaborated on. For example, this leads to a different definition of
variance than what might be seen elsewhere (the &lt;code&gt;calculate_variance&lt;/code&gt; used in
this chapter is &lt;code&gt;statistics.pvariance&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;statistics.variance&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is good to see that a numerically stable definition of variance is used
here (see &lt;a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0450/"&gt;PEP 450&lt;/a&gt; for more
discussion on this). These numerical issues show why it is important to use a
real statistics library rather than a home grown one. In other words, use this
chapter to learn more about statistics and Python, but if you ever need to do
statistics on real data, use a statistics library like &lt;code&gt;statistics&lt;/code&gt; or
&lt;code&gt;numpy&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, I should note that this book appears to be written against
Python 3.3, whereas &lt;code&gt;statistics&lt;/code&gt; was added to the Python standard library in
Python 3.4. Perhaps it will get a mention in future editions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 4, "Algebra and Symbolic Math with SymPy" starts the introduction to
SymPy. The chapter starts similar to the
&lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/index.html"&gt;official SymPy tutorial&lt;/a&gt; in
describing what symbolics is, and guiding the reader away from common
misconceptions and gotchas. The chapter does a good job of explaining common
gotchas and avoiding antipatterns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This chapter may serve as an alternative to the official tutorial. Unlike the
official tutorial, which jumps into
&lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/simplification.html#powers"&gt;higher-level mathematics&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/matrices.html"&gt;broader use-cases&lt;/a&gt;,
this chapter may be better suited to those wishing to use SymPy from the
standpoint of high school mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only gripes with this chapter, which, in total, are minor, relate to printing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typesetting of the pretty printing is inconsistent and, in some cases,
incorrect. Powers are printed in the book using superscript numbers, like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, SymPy prints powers like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; 2
x
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;even when Unicode pretty printing is enabled. This is a minor point, but it
may confuse users. Also, the output appears to use ASCII pretty printing
(mixed with superscript powers), for example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    x   x   x   x
x + -- + -- + -- + --
    2    3    4    5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most users will either get MathJax printing (if they are using the Jupyter
notebook), or Unicode printing, like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;     2    3    4    5
    x    x    x    x
x +  +  +  + 
    2    3    4    5
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is a minor point, but at the very least the correct printing
looks better than the fake printing used here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In line with the previous point, I would recommend telling the user to
start with &lt;code&gt;init_printing()&lt;/code&gt;. The function is used once to change the order
of printing to rev-lex (for series printing). There is a link to the
&lt;a href="http://docs.sympy.org/latest/tutorial/printing.html"&gt;tutorial page on printing&lt;/a&gt;. That
page goes into more depth than is necessary for the book, but I would
recommend at least mentioning to always call &lt;code&gt;init_printing()&lt;/code&gt;, as 2-D
printing can make a huge difference over the default &lt;code&gt;str&lt;/code&gt; printing, and it
obviates the need to call &lt;code&gt;pprint&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 5, "Playing with Sets and Probability" covers SymPy's set objects
(particularly &lt;code&gt;FiniteSet&lt;/code&gt;) to do some basic set theory and probability. I'm
excited to see this in the book. The sets module in SymPy is relatively new,
but quite powerful. We do not yet have an introduction to the sets module in
the SymPy tutorial. This chapter serves as a good introduction to it (albeit
only with finite sets, but the SymPy functions that operate on infinite sets
are exactly the same as the ones that operate on finite sets). In all, I don't
have much to say about this chapter other than that I was pleasantly surprised
to see it included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 6 shows how to draw geometric shapes and fractals with matplotlib. I
again won't say much on this, as I am no matplotlib expert. The ability to
draw leaf fractals and Sierpiski triangles with Python does look
entertaining, and should keep readers enthralled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chapter 7, "Solving Calculus Problems" goes into more depth with SymPy. In
particular, assumptions, limits, derivatives, and integrals.  The chapter
alternates between symbolic formulations using SymPy and numeric
calculations (using &lt;code&gt;evalf&lt;/code&gt;). The numeric calculations are done both for
simple examples and more advanced things (like implementing gradient descent).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small gripe here. The book shows that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;from sympy import Symbol
x = Symbol('x')
if (x + 5) &amp;gt; 0:
    print('Do Something')
else:
    print('Do Something else')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;raises &lt;code&gt;TypeError&lt;/code&gt; at the evaluation of &lt;code&gt;(x + 5) &amp;gt; 0&lt;/code&gt; because its truth value
cannot be determined. The solution to this issue is given as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;x = Symbol('x', positive=True)
if (x + 5) &amp;gt; 0:
    print('Do Something')
else:
    print('Do Something else')
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; to be positive via &lt;code&gt;Symbol('x', positive=True)&lt;/code&gt; is correct, but
even in this case, evaluating an inequality may still raise a &lt;code&gt;TypeError&lt;/code&gt; (for
example, &lt;code&gt;if (x - 5) &amp;gt; 0&lt;/code&gt;). The better way to do this is to use &lt;code&gt;(x + 5).is_positive&lt;/code&gt;. This would require a bit more discussion, especially since
SymPy uses a three-valued logic for assumptions, but I do consider "if
&amp;lt;symbolic inequality&amp;gt;" to be a SymPy antipattern.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like Saha's approach in this chapter of first showing unevaluated forms
(&lt;code&gt;Limit&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Derivative&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Integral&lt;/code&gt;), and then evaluating them with
&lt;code&gt;doit()&lt;/code&gt;. This puts users in the mindset of a mathematical expression being a
formula which may or may not later be "calculated". The opposite approach,
using the function forms, &lt;code&gt;limit&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;diff&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;integrate&lt;/code&gt;, which evaluate if
they can and return an unevaluated object if they can't, can be confusing to
new users in my experience. A common new SymPy user question is (some form of)
"how do I evaluate an expression?" (the answer is &lt;code&gt;doit()&lt;/code&gt;). Saha's approach
avoids this question by showing &lt;code&gt;doit()&lt;/code&gt; from the outset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also like that this chapter explains the gotcha of &lt;code&gt;math.sin(Symbol('x'))&lt;/code&gt;,
although I personally would have included this earlier in the text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Side note: now that I look, these are both areas in which the official
tutorial could be improved).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book is a good introduction to doing math with Python, and, for the
chapters that use it, a good basic introduction to SymPy. I would recommend it
to anyone wishing to learn SymPy, but especially to anyone whose knowledge of
mathematics may preclude them from getting the most out of the official SymPy
tutorial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagine this book would work well as a pedagogical tool, either for math
teachers or for self-learners. The exercises in this book should push the
motivated to learn more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a few minor gripes, but no major issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can purchase this book from the
&lt;a href="https://www.nostarch.com/doingmathwithpython"&gt;No Starch Press&lt;/a&gt; website, both
as a print book or an ebook. The website also includes a sample chapter
(&lt;a href="https://www.nostarch.com/download/Doing%20Math%20with%20Python_sample_Chapter1.pdf"&gt;chapter 1&lt;/a&gt;),
code samples from the book, and exercise solutions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/doing-math-with-python-by-amit-saha-book-review/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 21:01:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lessons learned from working at Continuum</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last Friday was my last day working at Continuum Analytics. I enjoyed my
time at the company, and wish success to it, but the time has come for me to
move on. Starting later this year, I will start working with
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/scopatz"&gt;Anthony Scopatz&lt;/a&gt; at his new lab
&lt;a href="http://www.ergs.sc.edu/index.html"&gt;ERGS&lt;/a&gt; at the University of South
Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During my time at Continuum (over two years if you count a summer internship),
I primarily worked on the
&lt;a href="https://www.continuum.io/downloads"&gt;Anaconda distribution&lt;/a&gt; and its open
source package manager, &lt;a href="http://conda.pydata.org/"&gt;conda&lt;/a&gt;.  I learned a lot of
lessons in that time, and I'd like to share some of them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Left to their own devices, people will make the minimal possible solution to
  packaging. They won't try to architect something. The result will be
  over-engineered, specific to their use-case, and lack reproducibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to ensure that some software has no bugs is for it to have many
  users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be wary of the "software would be great if it weren't for all the users"
  mentality (cf. the previous point).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people don't code defensively. If you are working on a project that
  requires extreme stability, be cautious of contributions from those outside
  the development team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hostility towards Windows and Windows users doesn't help anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/593170976981913600"&gt;https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/593170976981913600&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a software updater, stability is the number one priority. If the updater
  breaks, how can a fix be deployed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you configure your program to update itself every time it runs you
  will still get bug reports with arbitrarily old versions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Separating components into separate git repositories leads to a
  philosophical separation of concerns among the components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone who isn't an active developer on the project will ignore this
  separation and open issues in the wrong repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid object oriented programming when procedural programming will do just
  fine.&lt;sup id="fnref4-fn1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open source is more about the open than the source. Develop things in the
  open, and you will create a community that respects you.&lt;sup id="fnref3-fn1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academics (often) don't know good software practices, nor good licensing
  practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither do some large corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Avoid over-engineering things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Far fewer people than I would have thought understand the difference between
  hard links and soft links.&lt;sup id="fnref-fn2"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn2"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changelogs are useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Semantic versioning is over-hyped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you make something and release it, the first version should be 1.0 (not
  0.1 or 0.0.1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting a difficult package to compile is like hacking a computer. All it
  takes is time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It doesn't matter how open source friendly your business is, there will
  always be people who will be skeptical and point their fingers at the
  smallest proprietary components, fear monger, and overgeneralize unrelated
  issues into FUD. These people should generally be ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't feed the trolls.&lt;sup id="fnref2-fn1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People constantly misspell the name of
  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/asmeurer/status/618595687958122496"&gt;Apple's desktop operating system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People always assume you have way more automation than you really do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Python standard library is not a Zen garden. Some parts of it are
  completely broken, and if you need to rely on them, you'll have to rewrite
  them. &lt;code&gt;shutil.rmtree&lt;/code&gt; on Windows is one example of this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux is strictly backwards compatible. Windows is strictly forwards
  compatible. &lt;sup id="fnref-fn3"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn3"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Linux, things tend to be very simple. On Windows, things tend to be very
  complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't decide about OS X. It lies somewhere in between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nobody uses 32-bit Linux. Why do we even support that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People oversimplify the problem of solving for package dependencies in their
  heads.  No one realizes that it's meaningless to say something like "the
  dependencies of NumPy" (every build of every version of NumPy has its own
  set of dependencies, which may or may not be the same).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing a set of rules and a solver to solve against those rules is
  relatively easy. Writing heuristics to tell users why those rules are
  unsolvable when they are is hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAT solvers solve NP-complete problems in general, but they can be very fast
  to solve common case problems. &lt;sup id="fnref-fn1"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fn-fn1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the smartest people I know, who otherwise make very rational and
  intelligent decisions,
  &lt;a href="https://asmeurer.github.io/python3-presentation/slides.html"&gt;refuse to update to Python 3&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an introvert, the option of working from home is great for maintaining
  sanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/a-developers-second-most-important-asset/"&gt;Aeron chairs are awesome&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If living in Austin doesn't turn you into a foodie you will at least gain a
  respect for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter, if used correctly, is a great way to interact with your users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter is also a great place to learn new things. Follow
  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JohnDCook"&gt;John Cook&lt;/a&gt; and
  &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/worrydream"&gt;Bret Victor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to make heavily shared content is to make it about git
  (at least if you're an expert).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good optimization algorithm avoids getting caught in local maxima by
  trying different parts of the search space that initially appear to be
  worse. The same approach should be taken in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-fn1"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are things that I already knew, but were reiterated.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref-fn1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref2-fn1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref3-fn1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref4-fn1" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-fn2"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are one of those people, I have a small presentation that
   explains the difference &lt;a href="https://speakerdeck.com/asmeurer/hard-links-and-soft-links"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref-fn2" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn-fn3"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These terms can be confusing, and I admit I got this backwards the
    first time I wrote this. According to Wikipedia,
    &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forward_compatibility"&gt;forwards compatible&lt;/a&gt;
    means a system can accept input intended for a later version of itself
    and
    &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backward_compatibility"&gt;backwards compatible&lt;/a&gt;
    means a system can accept input intended for an earlier version of
    itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I specifically mean here is that in terms of building packages
for Linux or Windows, for Linux, you should build a package on the
oldest version that you wish to support. That package will work on
newer versions of Linux, but not anything older (generally due to the
version of libc you are linked against).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, on Windows, you can can compile things on the
newest version (I used Windows 8 on my main Windows build VM), and it
will work on older versions of Windows like XP (as long as you ship
the right runtime DLLs). This is also somewhat confusing because
Windows tends to be both forwards compatible &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; backwards
compatible.&lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/#fnref-fn3" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/lessons-learned-from-working-at-continuum/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 22:29:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Python Trickery</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/python-trickery/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are some bits of Python trickery that I have come across. Each of the
following is invalid syntax.  See if you can figure out why&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;1 + not(2)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;f(*(
i for i in range(10)
if i % 2),
x=3,)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/python-trickery/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 19:11:46 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Playing with Swift and SpriteKit</title><link>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/playing-with-swift-and-spritekit/</link><dc:creator>Aaron Meurer</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I've always wanted to learn how to write native apps for iOS and the Mac as
long as either has existed.  However, the barrier of entry has always been too
high, given that I only ever had time to play with them as a hobby.  The
Objective-C programming language is a bit complicated to learn, especially
alongside all the memory management that you have to do (and it doesn't help
that Apple has gone through several memory management schemes through Mac OS X
versions).  To add on to that, the Cocoa framework is huge, and it's quite
daunting to even know where to get started with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Apple's announcement of the
&lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/"&gt;Swift programming language&lt;/a&gt; in June, it
was clear to me that the language would significantly lower the barrier of
entry.  The &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/xcode/downloads/"&gt;XCode 6 beta&lt;/a&gt; is
now public (i.e., you do not need to have a paid Apple Developer account to
access it), so anyone can play with Swift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I am still &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; new to both Swift and iOS development in general,
so it's quite likely that some of the things I mention here are actually bad
ideas.  If you know more than I do and spot a bad thing that I am doing,
please mention it in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also possible that some of the assumptions I've made about the Swift
language or the SpriteKit framework are actually wrong. Please remember that I
am still a beginner and take what I say with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Swift Language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't know how to program at all, I don't know how well this will work
for you. I already know several language, especially Python, so my experience
derives from that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, read through the
&lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/resources/"&gt;Swift language guide&lt;/a&gt;. If you
have XCode 6, you can read it interactively as a Playground. I only have read
through the first part so far, which gives a high-level overview of the
language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Swift language is actually quite easy to learn, especially if you already
know a high-level language like Python.  A few important things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; seem a bit confusing.  The difference is actually quite
simple: &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; denotes a variable that can change and &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; denotes a
variable that cannot.  You could in theory just use &lt;code&gt;var&lt;/code&gt; for everything,
but &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt; lets the compiler spot mistakes for you, and it also probably lets
it make your code faster.  If you intend to never change the value of a
variable, use &lt;code&gt;let&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swift uses type inference, meaning that you usually don't need to specify
types. But when you do, you do so by putting a &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; after the variable name,
like &lt;code&gt;var a: Int = 2&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;func f(a: Int)&lt;/code&gt;.  The exception is the return type
of a function, which uses the arrow &lt;code&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (if you are familiar with Python 3
type annotations, the syntax is exactly the same), &lt;code&gt;func f(a: Int) -&amp;gt; Int&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swift uses &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; after a type name to indicate that a variable could be its
given type, or &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;. If you are familiar with Haskell, this is like the
Maybe monad.  I know very little Haskell, so I don't know if Swift's
implementation of &lt;code&gt;?&lt;/code&gt; is truly a Monad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roughly speaking, in many circumstances, you don't know if a variable will
actually be the given type or not. A good example of this is with
dictionaries. &lt;code&gt;var a: [String: Int]&lt;/code&gt; creates a dictionary that maps
strings to integers. If you manipulate this dictionary, and then access a
key from it, like &lt;code&gt;a[b]&lt;/code&gt;, there is no way for the compiler to know if that
key will really be in the dictionary. If the key is in the dictionary, you
will get the value of that key. Otherwise, you will get &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;. Hence, the
type of &lt;code&gt;a[b]&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;Int?&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swift uses &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; to indicate that the value is not &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;, which tells the
compiler to compile code that doesn't check for that case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the most part, you can ignore this as well, at least when you
start. Just write code as you would, let XCode add in the types for you, and
only worry about types if the compiler tells you something is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swift functions often require the parameters be named, for instance, you
have to write &lt;code&gt;CGSize(width: 1, height: 2)&lt;/code&gt; instead of just &lt;code&gt;CGSize(1, 2)&lt;/code&gt;. This is both for clarity (the former is much easier to read if you
aren't familiar with the API for &lt;code&gt;CGSize&lt;/code&gt;), and because Swift allows
polymorphism, i.e., you can define different initializers for the same class
with different type signatures. For example, &lt;code&gt;CGRect&lt;/code&gt; can be initialized as
&lt;code&gt;CGRect(origin: CGPoint, size: CGSize)&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;CGRect(x: Int, y: Int, width: Int, height: Int)&lt;/code&gt;. This can lead to ambiguities in some cases unless you
explicitly tell the compiler which version to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've found Swift to be a very strict language. I don't mean this in the sense
described by
&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strict_programming_language"&gt;this Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;. What
I mean is that Swift typically only lets you do things one way.  This is
similar to Python's "one way to do it," except Swift enforces this at the
language level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A nice example of this is that I rarely get a warning from the Swift compiler.
Just about every message I've gotten from the compiler has been an error. The
difference is that the program will still compile and run with a warning. This
is different from C, C++, and Objective-C, which have many warnings that the
compiler will still compile with. These warnings usually are for things like
an incorrect pointer type. Since there is really only one type in C, the
integer (because all data in memory is just integers), the program can still
run even if you mix your types up a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also many cases where Swift seems maybe too strict about things,
although it's clear that it is doing it to try to stray people away from
common mistakes and antipatterns. For example, the condition of an &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt;
statement in Swift must always be of type &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;. Unlike languages like
Python, things do not have implicit boolean values. &lt;code&gt;if 1&lt;/code&gt; is a syntax
error. So is &lt;code&gt;if a&lt;/code&gt; unless &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; is type &lt;code&gt;Bool&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ends up not being a big problem. The things Swift forces you to do feel
like good programming practices.  This is not unlike how Python "forces" you
to keep your code indented correctly.  It feels very different from a language
like Java, where the things that you are forced to do all feel like they are
there simply to make the compiler writer's life easier.  And indeed, unlike
Java and Objective-C and much like Python, Swift code requires very little
boilerplate.  There are no header files for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all said and done, I like Swift. I don't like it as much as Python (I also
don't have my head wrapped around it as much as Python). But it's far better
than Objective-C, and that's what matters. Frankly, my biggest gripe with it
is the ubiquitous use of CamelCasing and two letter prefixing (&lt;code&gt;NS&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;CG&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code&gt;SK&lt;/code&gt;; I don't know if there's a name for this) in the API. I adamantly refuse
to do this with my own variables, because I believe CamelCase reduces
readability over underscore_casing. I like the Python convention to use
underscore_casing for variables, functions, and methods, and CamelCase for
classes (because classes are kind of like proper nouns, and CamelCase is as
close to Capitalization as possible in programming language conventions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn to read Objective-C&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is not necessary to write Objective-C any more, it is a good idea to
know how to read it. The reason is that a lot of good resources on the
internet are still in Objective-C (also a lot of Apple's example
documentation). The API names are the same, so this mainly boils down to
understanding how to convert the basic syntax to Swift. Reading the section of
the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objective_C#Syntax"&gt;Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; on
the syntax of Objective-C should be enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-objective-c"&gt;[touch locationInNode:self]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;would be translated to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;touch.locationInNode(self)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Use XCode&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are comfortable with the Swift language itself, you should get started
with a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, you should use XCode to edit your code, at least to begin with,
even if you are accustomed to using another editor.  The reason is that XCode
is going to do a lot of things for you which will make your life easier and
reduce the complexity significantly as you get started.  Once you are
comfortable, you can move to another editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things that XCode will do for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Autocompletion&lt;/strong&gt;: The best way to figure out the Cocoa APIs is to use the
autocompletion. This pops up when you want to override a method in a
subclass, create an object from an existing class, access an attribute of a
class, or instantiate a class or call a function (remember that Swift is
polymorphic, so it's useful to know all the possible ways to instantiate a
class or call a function).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compiler errors and warnings&lt;/strong&gt;: Swift, being a strictly typed language,
will give you a lot of useful compiler errors. It's pretty hard to write a
program incorrectly from a type point of view, and have it even compile.
XCode integrates this nicely, and it even offers suggestions on how to fix
things every once in a while (so that you can just click the button and have
it fixed inline).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Direct interaction with the iOS Simulator&lt;/strong&gt;: One button will compile your code
and start the simulator. If your target is Mac OS X, it will open the
application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Debugger&lt;/strong&gt;: Clicking to the left of a line will set a breakpoint in the
debugger.  The Swift debugger seems pretty limited right now. I wasn't able
to get any useful information out of the variables view when I used it.  But
in my experience using XCode in the past to debug C, its graphical debugger
is one of the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuration settings&lt;/strong&gt;: If you click on the XCode project in the files
view (the root node of all the files), you get a view with all the different
settings for your project. Most of these you probably won't want to change,
but a few are important, like what devices and orientations you want to
allow, what operating system versions you want to support, and the name and
version of your project.  Editing these outside of XCode requires editing an
XML file, which is no fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, any editor can potentially do these things, and I'm really looking
forward to the point where I can just use Emacs to edit Swift code, as the
XCode editor as an editor is quite annoying.  XCode was the editor that I used
before I switched to using Emacs, and it's not gotten much better. There are
still several visual glitches in the editor environment, especially with the
scope coloring and syntax highlighting. You can edit the keyboard shortcuts in
the XCode setting to get some things the way you like them (although I found
that trying to set TAB to autoindent did not work). You can also use a tool
like &lt;a href="https://pqrs.org/osx/karabiner/"&gt;Karabiner&lt;/a&gt; (previously
KeyRemap4MacBook) to enable Vim or Emacs editor shortcuts everywhere
(including XCode). It doesn't help that XCode 6 is still in beta (at some
point the editor backend died and all syntax highlighting and tab completion
stopped working; I managed to fix it by removing a spurious &lt;code&gt;!&lt;/code&gt; in the code)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The iOS Simulator&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One disappointing thing that I learned is that you cannot run any iOS program
you write on an iOS device unless you are in the paid developer program (or if
you Jailbreak and are willing to go through some hoops). The iOS developer
program costs $100 a year, and since I'm not sure yet how far I am going to go
with this, I am holding off on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other option then is to run on the simulator. The simulator is fine,
the only issue is that there are limits to how you can simulate a touch screen
on a computer with a mouse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things to note about the simulator:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several things you can do with the "hardware" from the hardware
menu, such as rotating the device or pressing the home button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's worth remembering the keyboard shortcut for pressing the home button,
H, as you can press it twice in quick succession just like on a real
device to open the task manger. You can then drag your app up to completely
reset it, without having to restart the simulator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The retina iPad is taller than your display, even if you have a 15" retina
display. So be aware that you will need to scroll up and down to see it
all. Alternately, you can use a smaller device, like an iPhone, or rotate it
to landscape, where it all fits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way to do multitouch is to hold down the Option key. This will
create two fingers.  However, it's quite limited as the two fingers are
always centered around the center of the screen. Therefore if you want to
test multitouching two objects, you'll have to position them symmetrically so
that you can grab them both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting started with a project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to start is to start a template project with XCode. I personally
started with a SpriteKit game for iOS. This created a basic template "Hello
World" Swift file with the basic &lt;code&gt;SKScene&lt;/code&gt; subclass. Go ahead and compile and
run this in the simulator to see what it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are four important methods of &lt;code&gt;SKScene&lt;/code&gt; which you will want to override,
&lt;code&gt;didMoveToView&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;touchesBegan&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;touchesEnded&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt;. &lt;code&gt;didMoveToView&lt;/code&gt;
is the initializer for the scene.  Anything that should be set up and appear
from the very beginning should go there. &lt;code&gt;touchesBegan&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;touchesEnded&lt;/code&gt; are
called when a finger touches the screen and when it leaves the screen,
respectively. Remember always that iOS devices are multitouch devices, so
these events can happen concurrently, and there can be multiple touches
happening at once.  The first argument to these methods is a set of touches,
which you should iterate over to perform actions (the "Hello World" example
shows how to do this). Finally, the &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; method is called every time the
scene is updated, at each "frame" essentially.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are other methods, for instance, &lt;code&gt;touchesMoved&lt;/code&gt;. However, I discovered
that you don't actually want to use &lt;code&gt;touchesMoved&lt;/code&gt; to do what you would think
you'd use it for, namely, to move stuff around. The reason is that there is no
easy way to sync up multitouches between &lt;code&gt;touchesBegan&lt;/code&gt; (where you know what
thing the finger started on) and &lt;code&gt;touchesMoved&lt;/code&gt; to move it around. It works
well for a single touch, but if you want to be able to move multiple things
around at once (which I highly recommend, as it leads to a much nicer user
experience), you have to do things a little differently, as I'll explain
below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding some objects to your environment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of classes to create various objects of various shapes. I
started with &lt;code&gt;SKSpriteNode&lt;/code&gt;, which creates a simple square, because I wanted
to play around with touch events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started out with four sprites (yes, it would be better to put these in an
array, and probably abstract them to a method):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;let sprite1 = SKSpriteNode(color: UIColor(red: 1.0, green: 0.0, blue: 0.0, alpha: 1.0), size: CGSize(width: 30, height: 30))
let sprite2 = SKSpriteNode(color: UIColor(red: 0.0, green: 1.0, blue: 0.0, alpha: 1.0), size: CGSize(width: 30, height: 30))
let sprite3 = SKSpriteNode(color: UIColor(red: 0.0, green: 0.0, blue: 1.0, alpha: 1.0), size: CGSize(width: 30, height: 30))
let sprite4 = SKSpriteNode(color: UIColor(red: 1.0, green: 1.0, blue: 0.0, alpha: 1.0), size: CGSize(width: 30, height: 30))
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These lines go at the class level. This lets them be accessed from within any
method of the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I could not figure out how to do was how to access class variables
from within other class variables.  In Python, you can do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-py"&gt;class Test:
    a = 1
    b = a + 1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in Swift, if you do&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;class Test {
    let a = 1
    let b = a + 1
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it tells you that &lt;code&gt;Test.Type does not have a member named 'a'&lt;/code&gt; on the &lt;code&gt;let b = a + 1&lt;/code&gt; line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have to use properties with getters and setters in this case, which I
didn't feel like fooling with. The result is that I did not abstract out the
&lt;code&gt;CGSize(width: 30, height: 30)&lt;/code&gt; into a common variable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;didMoveToView&lt;/code&gt; method then becomes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func didMoveToView(view: SKView) {
    let center = CGPoint(x:CGRectGetMidX(self.frame), y:CGRectGetMidY(self.frame))

    for s in [sprite1, sprite2, sprite3, sprite4] {
        s.position = center

        self.addChild(s)
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;self.addChild&lt;/code&gt; is the most important method here, as it actually puts the
sprite in the main view. If you forget this line, none of the sprites will
show up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you run this, you will only see the yellow box, because you put them all on
top of one another in the center of the view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/galleries/swift-game-1.png" width="500"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Adding Basic Physics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could change the positions so that they do not overlap, but the option I
went with was to play around with the physics a little. &lt;code&gt;SpriteKit&lt;/code&gt; has a nice
2D physics engine built in, and it's quite easy to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So my final &lt;code&gt;didMoveToView&lt;/code&gt; was&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func didMoveToView(view: SKView) {
    /* Setup your scene here */
    let center = CGPoint(x:CGRectGetMidX(self.frame), y:CGRectGetMidY(self.frame))

    for s in [sprite1, sprite2, sprite3, sprite4] {
        s.position = center

        var physics_body = SKPhysicsBody(rectangleOfSize: CGSize(width: 30, height: 30))

        physics_body.affectedByGravity = false
        physics_body.allowsRotation = false

        s.physicsBody = physics_body
        self.addChild(s)
    }

}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For each sprite, I create an &lt;code&gt;SKPhysicsBody&lt;/code&gt; with the exact same size as the
&lt;code&gt;SKSpriteNode&lt;/code&gt;s (there's probably a more direct way to do this), and attach it
to that node. The &lt;code&gt;affectedByGravity&lt;/code&gt; property is important. If you don't set
it to &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, all the objects will fall off the bottom of the screen. I
disabled &lt;code&gt;allowsRotation&lt;/code&gt; because I wanted my squares to stay
upright. Otherwise when when the squares hit one another they will rotate in
space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now &lt;code&gt;SceneKit&lt;/code&gt; will prevent the squares from overlapping with one another, even
if we put them on top of each other as we have done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So now when we start the simulator, we see&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/galleries/swift-game-2.png" width="500"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making the squares movable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, let's make it so that we can move these squares around.  The correct way
to do this took me some time to figure out.  I finally got some hints from
&lt;a href="http://eppz.eu/blog/spritekit-drag/"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key thing here is that the &lt;code&gt;UITouch&lt;/code&gt; objects remain the same objects for
the duration of the touch. Their position is updated when the touch
moves. Hence, you just need to associate each touch with the node that was
touched when the touch began, and move the node to the position of that touch
with each update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, we will create a dictionary on the class mapping touches to nodes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;var selected: [UITouch: SKNode] = [:]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, in the &lt;code&gt;touchesBegan&lt;/code&gt; method, map every touch to the node that it
touches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func touchesBegan(touches: NSSet, withEvent event: UIEvent) {
    /* Called when a touch begins */

    selected = [:]
    for touch: AnyObject in touches {
        let location = touch.locationInNode(self)

        selected[touch as UITouch] = nodeAtPoint(location)

    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;as UITouch&lt;/code&gt; part is needed because the compiler only knows that touch is
&lt;code&gt;AnyObject&lt;/code&gt;. This was one of the things that was helpfully suggested by the
compiler, so I did not really need to know what I was doing to get it right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that even if you touch the background behind the squares, you are still
touching a node, namely, the &lt;code&gt;GameScene&lt;/code&gt; node itself (the node for the class
you are working on).  This is a very important observation, as it will tell us
how to get the right position for the node when we update it. It also means
that we should keep track of which nodes we actually want to be moved by the
touch. Trying to move the &lt;code&gt;GameScene&lt;/code&gt; node is ignored, at leads to a lot of
console logs, so we should avoid it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, let's write the &lt;code&gt;touchesEnded&lt;/code&gt; method. This method is simple. If a touch
ends (the finger is removed from the screen), we should remove it from the
&lt;code&gt;selected&lt;/code&gt; dictionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func touchesEnded(touches: NSSet, withEvent event: UIEvent) {
    for touch: AnyObject in touches {
    selected[touch as UITouch] = nil
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To delete an item from a dictionary in Swift, just set it to &lt;code&gt;nil&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, finally, we need to write the &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt; method to move the node to the
current position of the touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest way to do this is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func update(currentTime: CFTimeInterval) {
    /* Called before each frame is rendered */
    for (touch, node) in selected {
        if !contains([sprite1, sprite2, sprite3, sprite4], node) {
            continue
        }
        let location = touch.locationInNode(self)
        node.position = location
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that we only modify the position for the four sprite nodes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;touch.locationInNode(self)&lt;/code&gt; part took me a long time to figure out. There
are other methods, like &lt;code&gt;touch.locationInView(nil)&lt;/code&gt;, but this does something
very strange where the the horizontal axis was doubled (moving the touch one
inch moved the object two inches), and the vertical axis was inverted. If
someone knows what was going on there, please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modifying the position directly is nice, but it's nice to play around a little
bit with a third thing from SpriteKit, actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we will do instead of setting the position of the node is to tell
SpriteKit to move the node there in a certain amount of time. If we make this
time small enough, like &lt;code&gt;0.01&lt;/code&gt; seconds, it will appear to act exactly the
same. If we up this time, there will be a smooth "lag" where the node catches
up to the touch. Because the movement always happens in the same amount of
time, it will move faster if the finger is farther away. This gives the
squares a nice "frictioney" effect with some springiness to it, which is quite
nice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="language-swift"&gt;override func update(currentTime: CFTimeInterval) {
    /* Called before each frame is rendered */
    for (touch, node) in selected {
        if !contains([sprite1, sprite2, sprite3, sprite4], node) {
            continue
        }
        let location = touch.locationInNode(self)
        let action = SKAction.moveTo(location, duration: 0.1)
        node.runAction(SKAction.repeatAction(action, count: 1))
    }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many other actions we can perform, like rotations and color
changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of the movement. You can see it works even with
multitouch.  You can also see the collision physics cause the other squares to
move out of the way when another square hits them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/SpriteKit-Example.mp4" autoplay width="500" loop&gt;
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here you can see the movement lag caused by using &lt;code&gt;SKAction.moveTo&lt;/code&gt; with
&lt;code&gt;duration: 0.1&lt;/code&gt; (note that the mouse itself jumps a bit at the beginning, but
this is due to lag in the recording).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;video src="https://asmeurer.com/blog/SpriteKit-Example-2.mp4" autoplay width="500" loop&gt;
Your browser does not support the video tag.
&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have uploaded the full code to
&lt;a href="https://github.com/asmeurer/GameTest/blob/blog/GameTest/GameScene.swift"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't exactly a "game", but it does lay down the foundations for what you
would need to write a game in Swift using SpriteKit.  At least for me, it
shows me the technical basics of how to write some games that I had thought
about, which mostly involve making shapes and moving them around the screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  func Haskell CGSize CGRect CGPoint locationInNode SKScene
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  touch.locationInNode Karabiner KeyRemap4MacBook SpriteKit
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  didMoveToView touchesBegan touchesEnded touchesMoved py
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  SKSpriteNode sprite1 UIColor sprite2 sprite3 sprite4 'a'
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  Test.Type SKView CGRectGetMidX self.frame CGRectGetMidY
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  s.position self.addChild img src SKPhysicsBody SceneKit
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  rectangleOfSize body.affectedByGravity body.allowsRotation
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  s.physicsBody affectedByGravity allowsRotation UITouch
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  SKNode NSSet withEvent UIEvent AnyObject nodeAtPoint
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  GameScene currentTime CFTimeInterval node.position
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  frictioney SKAction.moveTo node.runAction autoplay
 --&gt;
&lt;!--  LocalWords:  SKAction.repeatAction
 --&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://asmeurer.com/blog/posts/playing-with-swift-and-spritekit/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Aug 2014 16:31:11 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>